<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0" 
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
  xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">

<channel>
<title>Fall-Winter 2002-2003</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</link>
<description></description>
<dc:language>en-us</dc:language>
<dc:creator></dc:creator>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T07:01:00-05:00</dc:date>
<admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://www.movabletype.org/?v=2.661" />
<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
<sy:updateBase>2000-01-01T12:00+00:00</sy:updateBase>

<item>
<title>Editors&apos; Introduction: Community Technology in a Post 9-11 World (Part II)</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000099.html</link>
<description> Submitting articles to the Review The editors welcome the submission of new material on an on-going basis and are committed to working with first-time authors as well as experienced writers to produce well-written pieces covering key developments and resources...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">99@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>ComTechReview</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T07:01:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fred Johnson Comes to UMass/Boston</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000100.html</link>
<description>Despite the entanglements that accompany a move to a new area and a new job (in this case, finding housing and wading through the university&apos;s red tape), Fred Johnson is quickly finding his niche in the Boston area and on...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">100@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>ComTechReview</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T07:00:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>CTCNet Update</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000104.html</link>
<description> Remembering CTCNet Founder Toni Stone On Thursday, November 21, CTCNet founder Toni Stone died. The notice posted on the CTCNet members list the next day and elsewhere has been followed up by scores of testimonials, including a remembrance on...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">104@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>CTCNet</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T06:01:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>The CTC Support Project: Local Support, National Implications</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000102.html</link>
<description> CTC Support Project Places Technical Volunteers for MIT CityDays Marissa Martin Forty-five MIT students volunteered at Boston-area CTCs on August 30, 2002, as part of a joint CTCNet Service Learning and MIT CityDays event. (MIT CityDays is a project...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">102@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>CTCNet</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T06:00:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>AFCN Update</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000150.html</link>
<description> As reported on the AFCN email list, results of the 2002 Board of Directors balloting were announced in July. Group members re-elected Ann Bishop, Richard Lowenberg, and Gene Crick to second terms on the board. Sally Rawlins, respected CN...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">150@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>AFCN</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T05:01:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Rise of the Knowledge Democracy</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000105.html</link>
<description> Technology should and must support human relationships. Many rural and inner city communities face a situation in which reliance on traditional methods of community planning and decision-making have resulted in shrinking communities with a constant outflow of the young...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">105@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>AFCN</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T05:00:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Summer Camp in Columbia, SC: Community Style</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000108.html</link>
<description><![CDATA[ Fast Forward is a community technology center housed at Hand Middle School in Columbia, South Carolina.&nbsp; In its three years, Fast Forward has developed a reputation for quality summer camps for children. Each year, the demand has increased, although...]]></description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">108@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>Profiles</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T04:05:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>ScienceQuest for Youth: A Growing Program</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000109.html</link>
<description> Our goals for all of our youth are the following: we want each child that enters our center to leave with self-confidence, healthy self-esteem, skills associated with social competency, and understanding of the new technology. We find that our...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">109@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>Profiles</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T04:04:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Transforming Rural Alaska through Wireless Technology in the Schools and Community</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000110.html</link>
<description><![CDATA[ In remote Alaskan villages, the public school is usually the center of the community.&nbsp; Often the largest building, the school frequently functions as a town meeting hall, a recreation center, the town library, and&#8212;in the past few years&#8212;the technology...]]></description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">110@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>Profiles</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T04:03:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mapping and Community Organizing in Philadelphia</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000112.html</link>
<description>Since 1995, the Philadelphia Association of Community Development Corporation (PACDC) has used wireless handheld technology for its member CDCs&apos; neighborhood-based data collection efforts. Early in 2001, PACDC launched a more ambitious program, acquiring a small fleet of Compaq iPAQ Pocket...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">112@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>Profiles</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T04:02:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Edna Jackson, Technology And Community Building: From Staunchest Opponent to Greatest Proponent</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000113.html</link>
<description> This article shares the case study of one individual in her efforts to achieve social and cultural resonance with technology. She is a participant in the Creating Community Connections (C3) Project,* an ongoing effort at Camfield Estates, a predominantly...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">113@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>Profiles</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T04:01:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>From The Children&apos;s Partnership: Strategies and Resources for Community Technology Practitioners</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000107.html</link>
<description>The Children&apos;s Partnership (TCP) is a national child advocacy organization that undertakes research, demonstration programs, and advocacy campaigns to help ensure that low-income and other underserved communities benefit from the &quot;digital revolution.&quot; Over the past three years, the Children&apos;s Partnership...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">107@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>Profiles</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T04:00:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Sweet, Sweet $ustainability</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000114.html</link>
<description><![CDATA[My work brings me into contact with hundreds of Washington State-based community technology programs (&quot;CTPs&quot;), and they are all working on serious sustainability issues. I work on the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation's Community Access to Technology (CAT) Program, and...]]></description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">114@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>TA to Nonprofits</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T03:02:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Online Fundraising Comes of Age</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000115.html</link>
<description><![CDATA[Many of us recall the announcement by President Bush, encouraging Americans from all walks of life to visit Helping.org, RedCross.org and other online sites to donate generously.&nbsp; According to a March 21, 2002, Chronicle of Philanthropy article by Nicole Wallace,...]]></description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">115@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>TA to Nonprofits</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T03:01:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>
<item>
<title>Unlocking the Potential of Open-Source</title>
<link>http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000116.html</link>
<description>Community building is fundamentally about local problems being solved at the local level by local stakeholders. What if we were to apply this philosophy to technology development in nonprofit organizations? Already, NPOs are building technology to support their needs. Organizations...</description>
<guid isPermaLink="false">116@http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/</guid>
<dc:subject>TA to Nonprofits</dc:subject>
<dc:date>2005-06-14T03:00:00-05:00</dc:date>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>