<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Summer 2004</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/" />
  <modified>2005-06-14T12:00:00Z</modified>
  <tagline></tagline>
  <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2007:/summer-2004//9</id>
  <generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="2.661">Movable Type</generator>
  <copyright>Copyright (c) 2005, anonymous</copyright>
  <entry>
    <title></title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000221.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T12:00:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T08:00:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.221</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T12:00:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Our cover features three of the people whose stories are told in Freedom Machines, a film about technology access for people with disabilities being shown at the conference, and community technology activists involved with conference presentations and CTCNet organizational development....</summary>
    <author>
      <name>anonymous</name>
      
      <email>peterm@igc.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Cover Info</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[Our cover features three of the people whose stories are told in <em><a href=#freedom">Freedom Machines</a></em>, a film about technology access for people with disabilities being shown at the conference, and community technology activists involved with conference presentations and CTCNet organizational development. Pictured here are Floyd Stewart, Shoshana Brand, and Susanna Sweeney-Martini surrounded by (clockwise) Angela Stuber, Erroll Reese, Mercedes Soto, Laura Breeden, and David Keyes. The back cover features the cast and crew of the Commonwealth Broadband Collaborative's "First Tuesday" monthly program and CTC VISTAs profiled from two of the shows: Liri Qirici with Malden (MA) Access Television and Jason Crow, Daniell Krawczyk, Amy McKenzie, and Erica Freshour with the Grand Rapids (MI) Community Media Center. More information about <em><a href=#freedom">Freedom Machines</a></em> is below.

<P>
<center><img src="winter-spring-2004/FM-Logo.gif"></center>
<P>
<a name="freedom">
<em>Freedom Machines</em>, a documentary that will be airing this fall on PBS and is being shown as a pre-conference event Thursday evening, explores the remarkable power that technology has to transform the lives of people with disabilities. The Alliance for Technology Access (ATA) has been very involved in the development of this film, with an award winning crew and Oscar-nominated producer. Shot in nine locations around the U.S &#8212; including several ATA centers &#8212; with characters ranging from 7 to 92 years of age, Freedom Machines is not only a revelation but also a call to action. The film's web site <a href="www.freedommachines.com">www.freedommachines.com</a> provides useful information to supplement the documentary both in educating people about disabilities and how technology and civil rights laws can bring us closer to a world that is more inclusive for everyone.]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Editors&apos; Introduction: East Side, West Side...</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000198.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T11:04:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T07:04:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.198</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T11:04:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"> From small gatherings and early conferences in New York and Boston, the Annual CTCNet Conference has grown in scope and traveled across the land, to Washington, DC, farther south to Atlanta and Austin and San Diego, through Pittsburgh and...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>anonymous</name>
      
      <email>peterm@igc.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>CTR &amp; CTCNet</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p>
From small gatherings and early conferences in New York and Boston, the Annual CTCNet Conference has grown in scope and traveled across the land, to Washington, DC, farther south to Atlanta and Austin and San Diego, through Pittsburgh and Chicago in the midwest, and now to the northwest, Seattle.
</p><p>
As the country's oldest and largest association of organizations providing technology access, education, and support to underserved communities, CTCNet represents programs ranging from basic access and support to advanced multimedia applications and wireless zones, from human services and community organizing to business and economic development.
</p><p>
The Annual CTCNet Conference reflects the diversity of the community technology movement, last year drawing attendance from nearly every state and twelve countries. It also reinforces the need to incorporate, rather than simply accommodate, the perspectives and talents of communities of color and people with disabilities. This year's pre-conference and schedule includes an added emphasis on disability access and assistive technology, including a special advance screening of the documentary <i>Freedom Machines</i>, scheduled to air nationally on PBS this fall.
</p><p>
Finally, in a world where daily organizational demands are generally overwhelming, the CTCNet conference represents one of the few community technology gatherings where there are reflective and thoughtful presentations and discussions that are then available in a repository for future use.  As with last year, when CTC VISTAs Melissa Daigle and Dan Schackman pulled together the first <a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/issue.php?issue_id=2">special issue of the <i>Community Technology Review</i></a> to supplement the 2003 DC national conference and offer a portal to its archives, this year's similar efforts by Dan Schackman, once again, along with Ryan Turner at CTCNet and Caroline Bennett, CTC VISTA and Assistant <i>Review</i> editor, provide a special dimension to the conference proceedings and gathering.  Like last year's issue, the articles and spotlights here and the links to the workshops that connect with presentation material provide not only a historical record of presenters and their resources, but a living archive to build upon and grow with. 
</p><p>
There are few conferences that we know of that are able to bring together so much that is testimony to the ongoing vitality of these kinds of gatherings.  Computer Professionals for Social Responsibility has supported a biannual gathering to examine Directions and Implications of Advanced Computing with a community technology perspective, and the DIAC proceedings are <a href="http://www.cpsr.org/conferences/conferences.html">summarized online</a> and are available in hardcopy.  The <a href="http://www.ntia.doc.gov/otiahome/top/research/research.htm">reports and evaluations</a> of the Department of Commerce's Technology Opportunities Program (TOP) are another special resource in this regard.  CTCNet's recent track record in documenting its lessons at these gatherings is exemplary.  Congratulations, once again. We're pleased to support this effort. --pm & rc
</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The 2004 CTCNet Conference</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000190.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T11:03:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T07:03:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.190</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T11:03:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"> The Annual CTCNet Conference provides an opportunity for people to share their organizational expertise and personal experiences towards a more active and informed community of interests. This year we are working to highlight the resources and model programs that...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Kavita Singh</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>CTR &amp; CTCNet</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p><table border="0" align="left" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="140" valign="top">
<center><img src="/summer-2004/img/CTCNetKavita.jpg" alt="Kavita Singh">
</center>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
The Annual CTCNet Conference provides an opportunity for people to share their organizational expertise and personal experiences towards a more active and informed community of interests.  This year we are working to highlight the resources and model programs that use technology in ways that inform and engage citizens and that contribute to community development.<br><br>
Community technology centers and programs continue to improve individual lives and foster healthy neighborhoods around the world. The capacity of the community technology field itself has grown to address a broader set of human needs and social priorities, including workforce development, education and literacy, youth media, immigration, health, public safety, housing, business and economic development, and civic engagement.
</p><p>
Community technology, in a relatively short period of time, has emerged as a vital social force that impacts the ways we think about, and act upon, the issues affecting our society. This year's meeting affords us a chance to recount our successes, recognize the diversity and creativity within our programs, and challenge ourselves to better address local community needs as we harness the power of people and technology to build connected communities.
</p><p>
<table border="0" align="right" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="140" valign="top">
<center><img src="/summer-2004/img/CTCNetlogo.gif" alt="CTCNet logo">
</center>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
We should never lose sight of basic needs within the core of our missions: equity in technology access and opportunities to acquire and apply technology skills. There is still much work to be done to ensure that vital information and communications technology tools and resources are affordable, accessible, and applicable to all people.  We hope to explore ways to sustain the momentum we have achieved while expanding the role for, and impact of, CTCs within the communities in which we work.</p><p>
We're looking forward to seeing you in Seattle and discussing the future of our field!<br>
--Kavita Singh, Executive Director]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome to Seattle</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000199.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T11:02:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T07:02:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.199</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T11:02:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">This year&apos;s CTCNet Conference in Seattle, Washington, brings us to the frontier of technology and strong community access. Washington State is famous for apples, airplanes, salmon, scenic wilderness, logging, and software. The same frontier spirit that promotes and protects these...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>David Keyes and Rhonda Evans and Mike Donlin</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>CTR &amp; CTCNet</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p>This year's CTCNet Conference in Seattle, Washington, brings us to the frontier of technology and strong community access. </p><p><table border="0" align="right" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1"><tbody><tr><td width="360" valign="top"><center><img src="/summer-2004/img/seattlemap.jpg" alt="Seattle Community Computer Access and Training Sites"></center></td></tr></tbody></table>Washington State is famous for apples, airplanes, salmon, scenic wilderness, logging, and software. The same frontier spirit that promotes and protects these assets may have also led to its deep immersion in community technology including public access TV, community networks, media arts, computer tech centers, leading library access, community Wi-Fi, and even community voice mail. On the business front <a href=" http://www.real.com/">Real Networks</a>, <a href="http://www.microsoft.com">Microsoft</a>, <a href="http://www.adobe.com">Adobe</a> and many more have homes here. Seattle is home to the <a href="http://www.washington.edu/">University of Washington</a>, the northwest stop on Internet2. The foundation community, including the <a href="http://www.gatesfoundation.org/">Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</a>, has been a strong supporter of technology literacy and integration efforts for libraries, schools, rural and urban areas.  Nearby Tacoma features <a href="http://www.click-network.com/">the Click! Network</a>, the municipally owned cable and broadband utility.</p><p><a href="http://www.jackstraw.org/">The Jack Straw Foundation</a> started as KRAB community radio in 1962 and now offers community audio access and training, including audio editing for visually impaired users. Public access TV centers in Seattle (now <a href="http://www.scantv.org/">SCAN</a>) and Olympia (<a href="http://www.tctv.net/">TCTV</a> started in 1982) have long been centers of community technology, and <a href="http://www.911media.org/">911 Media Arts</a> continues to pave the way for new media artists. The national <a href="http://www.cvm.org/">Community Voice Mail</a> began service in 1992. By 1996 Washington State had three community Free-Net networks:  the <a href="http://www.tcfn.org/">Columbia Free-Net</a>, <a href="http://www.tincan.org/">the Inland Northwest Community Access Network (TINCAN)</a>, and the <a href="http://www.scn.org/">Seattle Community Network</a>. All are still doing vital work, reaching urban and rural users with services including TINCAN's on-line Business Incubator. The WTO launched the worldwide <a href="http://www.indymedia.org">indymedia.org</a> community.  Now <a href="http://www.seattlewireless.net">Seattlewireless.net</a> leads a growing metropolitan community wireless network.</p><p>The <a href="http://www.cityofseattle.net/tech/techmap.htm">City of Seattle's tech map</a> lists over 160 community access points in and around the metropolitan area. There's a strong belief here in investing in diverse community-driven CTCs.  <a href="http://www.hud.gov/nnw/nnwindex.html">Neighborhood Networks'</a> development in the housing community grew up here, with Washington State's Digital Promise leading the way. Now the <a href="http://psact.org/">Puget Sound Alliance for Community Technology (PSACT)</a> brings together CTCs and supporters to improve service delivery. <a href="http://www.npower.org/">Npower</a> started here and continues to assist non-profits, while <a href="http://www.onenw.org/">One Northwest</a> serves the environmental movement, <a href="http://www.digitalpartners.org/">Digital Partners</a> works worldwide, and <a href="http://projectalchemy.org/">Project Alchemy</a> supports progressive applications of technology. </p><p>The City of Seattle provided public bulletin board access in 1995 and public Internet terminals a few years later. Seattle was the first in the nation to establish a community technology planner position, Technology Matching Fund and IT indicators. CTCs in the area receive strong support from the <a href="http://www.seattleschools.org/">Seattle Public Schools</a>, which has been involved in community technology since 1996 and is leading the way to a more systemic and systematic approach to connecting K-12 education and community technology efforts.</p><p>Community technology leaders from Washington state made significant contributions in planning the 2004 CTCNet Conference, as CTCNet engaged a local host committee including representatives from the City of Seattle, Seattle Public Schools, PSACT, the Seattle Public Library, the RECA Foundation, the Inland Northwest Community Access Network (TINCAN), <a href="http://www.seattleartmuseum.org/">the Seattle Art Museum</a>, and others, and the host committee is pleased to welcome the 2004 CTCNet Conference to Seattle! <hr>
<div class="bionote"><a href="mailto:david.keyes@ci.seattle.wa.us">David Keyes</a> directs the City of Seattle Department of Information Technology and is a CTCNet Board Member.  <a href="mailto:Revans@tcfn.org">Rhonda Evans</a> of the RECA Foundation and <a href="mailto:mdonlin@seattleschools.org">Mike Donlin</a> of the Seattle Public Schools also contributed to this piece.</div>]]>
      On Behalf of the Seattle Organizing Committee
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Toni Stone Innovative Initiative Awards</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000200.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T11:01:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T07:01:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.200</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T11:01:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"> Since 1996, CTCNet has presented the Innovative Initiative award to the leaders behind outstanding and innovative new programs, as a way of recognizing special contributions made by an individual at a CTCNet center, demonstrating innovation in the field and...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>anonymous</name>
      
      <email>peterm@igc.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>CTR &amp; CTCNet</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p>
<table border="0" align="right" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="110" valign="top">
<center><img src="/summer-2004/img/CTCNetToni.jpg" alt="Toni Stone">
</center>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
Since 1996, CTCNet has presented the Innovative Initiative award to the leaders behind outstanding and innovative new programs, as a way of recognizing special contributions made by an individual at a CTCNet center, demonstrating innovation in the field and a commitment to impacting people's lives. In 2003, the award was renamed the Toni Stone Innovative Initiative Award.  The award is presented each year at the Annual CTCNet Conference.
</p><p>
In a moving presentation at the 12th Annual Conference in Washington, DC, the founder of the award, Tim Barclay, gave the award to Jenny Pierce, praising her dedication and commitment to her work.  Jenny is Director of <a href="http://www.fight.org/critpath.asp">the AIDS Library and Critical Path Projects at Philadelphia FIGHT</a>.  These programs provide a continuum of services to people with HIV, those at high risk, and those living in communities at risk so that they are able to access the Internet, learn how to use this powerful tool to meet their own goals, and communicate with each other through personal email and discussion lists.
</p><p>
Previous recipients of the award are:
</p><p>
2002: <b>Dee Albritton</b><br>
<a href="http://www.ctcnet.org/stories/v2/15.html">Fast Forward</a><br>
Columbia, SC <br>
<br>
2001: <b>Karen Chi Chung</b><br>
<a href="http://www.bpsos.org/Camden%20Website%2012.9.02/index.htm">Boat People S.O.S.</a><br>
Camden, NJ<br>
<br>
2000: <b>Nancy Montana</b><br>
<a href="http://www.laplaza.org/">La Plaza Telecommunity Foundation</a><br>
Taos, NM<br>
<br>
1998-1999 (joint winners):<br>
<b>Jackie Ziglar</b><br>
<a href="http://www.garfieldchildsfund.org/">Garfield F. Childs Memorial Fund</a><br>
Richmond, VA <br>
<b>Bill Callahan</b><br>
<a href="http://www.ctcnet.org/resources/reports/casey/casey16.htm">West Side Community Computer Center</a><br>
Cleveland, OH<br>
<br>
1997: <b>Josh Merrow</b><br>
<a href="http://www.newvisions.org/schoolsuccess/samples/integration/ElPuenteoverview.shtml">El Puente Academy for Peace and Social Justice</a><br>
Brooklyn, NY<br>
<br>
1996: <b>Marcia Snowden</b><br>
<a href="http://hillhouse.ckp.edu/guide.html">New Beginnings Learning Center </a><br>
Pittsburgh, PA<br>
</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Pre-Conference Sessions</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000192.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T11:00:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T07:00:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.192</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T11:00:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Thanks to support from the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services Compassion Capital Fund, CTCNet is pleased to present an expanded slate of Pre-Conference workshops offering more in-depth exploration of issues and resources useful to our members&apos; work. This...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>anonymous</name>
      
      <email>peterm@igc.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>CTR &amp; CTCNet</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p>Thanks to support from the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services Compassion Capital Fund, CTCNet is pleased to present an expanded slate of Pre-Conference workshops offering more in-depth exploration of issues and resources useful to our members' work.<br><br>
This year, sessions include:</p><p> 
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=82">Access Aware: Making Your CTC Accessible to People with Disabilities</a></p><p>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=88">The Best of New & Old: Fundraising Strategies for CTCs</a></p><p>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=162">CTCs & Community Change: Tools & Strategies</a></p><p>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=83">The CTC VISTA Project: Supervisor Orientation & Training</a></p><p>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=87">ScienceQuest:  Successful After-School Learning</a></p><p>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=85">Curriculum Development for Youth Technology Programs: the YouthLearn Method</a></p><p>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=161">Incorporating Youth Multimedia for Social Change in Your Community Technology Program</a>
</p><p>
<i>Freedom Machines</i>, a documentary that will be airing this fall on PBS and is being shown as a pre-conference event Thursday evening, explores the remarkable power that technology has to transform the lives of people with disabilities. The Alliance for Technology Access (ATA) has been very involved in the development of this film, with an award-winning crew and Oscar-nominated producer. Shot in nine locations around the U.S--including several ATA centers--with characters ranging from 7 to 92 years of age, <i>Freedom Machines</i> is not only a revelation but also a call to action. <a href="http://www.freedommachines.com">The film's web site</a> provides useful information to supplement the documentary both in educating people about disabilities and how technology and civil rights laws can bring us closer to a world that is more inclusive for everyone.</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Emergence, Convergence, and Empowerment</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000188.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T10:03:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T06:03:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.188</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T10:03:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">While the latter part of the twentieth century witnessed a growth in alternatives to mainstream corporate media, the technological advances of the 1990&apos;s--particularly the arrival of the World Wide Web--signaled the delivery of increasingly narrow distribution of specialized content to...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Daniel Schackman</name>
      <url>www.comtechreview.org</url>
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Development</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p>While the latter part of the twentieth century witnessed a growth in alternatives to mainstream corporate media, the technological advances of the 1990's--particularly the arrival of the World Wide Web--signaled the delivery of increasingly narrow distribution of specialized content to more fragmented audiences. In response to a growing tide of content offerings that are detached from, if not dissonant with, the real world, a small but growing number of individuals around the world are turning to alternative sources of news and information.
</p><p>
A new form of media convergence is rising at the grassroots level, empowering communities by giving people the tools to express themselves. Community technology centers, community media centers, telecenters, and independent media centers serve as agents of progressive social change, providing computer labs and digital media training to connect individuals, interest groups, and institutions with their neighborhoods, harnessing their shared strength and collective wisdom to create media that reflect the circumstances and experiences of real people. A team of leading media artists and educators is introducing workshop attendees to the exciting possibilities of this movement, offering strategies and practical advice on how to participate as national and international sites of civic expression and media production.
</p><p>
<table border="0" align="left" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="105" valign="top">
<center><img src="/summer-2004/img/johnsonsmall.jpg" alt="Fred Johnson">
</center>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
Spearheading this initiative is Fred Johnson, an Associate Professor at the University of Massachusetts-Boston's College of Public and Community Service, in the <a href="http://cpcs.umb.edu/cmt/">Community Media and Technology program</a>.  Johnson is a media artist, educator, documentary maker, policy analyst, and a consultant in communications and development. He has received a Fulbright Fellowship for the Television Arts, producing and directing documentaries for the BBC and for public television in the US. Johnson previously directed the Digital Directions project, a national planning process focused on the impact of digitization on the media arts, funded by the Ford Foundation, for the National Alliance for Media Arts and Culture (NAMAC).  Johnson stresses that we are at a point in time when it is both possible and advisable to envision something other than a marginalized alternative media culture: "I can not let go of the idea that in this moment there may be an opportunity in the next few years to create the distribution systems, production and social practices and politics necessary for the creation of a much more robust, non-commercial media culture."
</p><p>
Other indy media leaders participating in this workshop include Nettrice Gaskins, Director of the <a href="http://www.cbcmedia.net/">Commonwealth Broadband Collaborative (CBC)</a>.  Gaskins has over ten years experience in multimedia/digital media, education/training, leadership, and program development, most recently as the director of the Multimedia Center at <a href="http://www.bnntv.org/">Boston Neighborhood Network (BNN)</a>. She has been a member of the CBC steering committee since its inception, is on the national board of CTCNet, and has developed online community media and technology courses for UMass Boston/College for Public and Community Service.  Gaskins states, "While new technologies such as wireless broadband and 'broadcatching' are emerging, convergence is creating virtual and actual environments where media makers are exploring ways to become more empowered."
</p><p>
In keeping with the theme of this year's Annual CTCNet Conference, this team is leading the way by showing how creative use of technology can help empower communities.  Independent community media are a vital resource.  At a time in which divergent and diffuse voices are being drowned out in mainstream media, the emergence of creative outlets and alternatives is crucial.  CTCs can be leaders in this movement, by using the resources that they already have, creatively using new tools, and understanding the transformational power that they have at hand.
</p><p>
<hr>
<TABLE cellSpacing=1 cellPadding=1 border=0 align=left>
<TD class=Normal vAlign=top width=150>
<P><IMG src="/summer-2004/img/schackman.gif" alt="Dan Schackman"></P>
</TD>
</TBODY></TABLE>
<div class="bionote">Dan Schackman has served as CTCNet's CTC AmeriCorps VISTA Member and Information Management Associate from June 2002-June 2004.</div></p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Community and Independent Media Organizations</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000201.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T10:02:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T06:02:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.201</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T10:02:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"> Alliance for Community Media (ACM) Independent Media Centers (IMCs) Independent Press Association (IPA) National Alliance for Media Arts &amp; Culture (NAMAC) Commonwealth Broadband Collaborative (CBC)...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>anonymous</name>
      
      <email>peterm@igc.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Development</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p><imgsrc="cmtbanner.jpg">
</p><p>
<a href="http://www.alliancecm.org">Alliance for Community Media (ACM)
</a></p><p>
<a href="http://www.indymedia.org">Independent Media Centers (IMCs)
</a></p><p>
<a href="http://www.indypress.org">Independent Press Association (IPA)
</a></p><p>
<a href="http://www.namac.org">National Alliance for Media Arts & Culture (NAMAC)
</a></p><p>
<a href="http://www.cbcmedia.net">Commonwealth Broadband Collaborative (CBC)
</p>]]>
      Additional Resources
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Community Development and Technology Track Sessions &amp; Presenters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000182.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T10:01:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T06:01:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.182</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T10:01:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">An Innovative Partnership: Aligning CTC efforts with the Community Building Movement Presented by: Vicky Glenzer – Gelatt, Oregon Center for Applied Science, Jennifer Gonzalez, Alamo Area Mutual Housing; Tony Fleming, Eastmont Computing Center Building Community from the Inside Out Presented...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>anonymous</name>
      
      <email>peterm@igc.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Development</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p><a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=101">An Innovative Partnership: Aligning CTC efforts with the Community Building Movement</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Vicky Glenzer – Gelatt, Oregon Center for Applied Science, Jennifer Gonzalez, Alamo Area Mutual Housing; Tony Fleming, Eastmont Computing Center
<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=145">Building Community from the Inside Out</a> 
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Ronda Evans, RECA Foundation
<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=105">Emergence, Convergence and Empowerment</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Fred Johnson, Umass Boston; Nettrice Gaskins, Commonwealth Broadband Collaborative (CBC); Dirk Koning, Grand Rapids Community Media Center
<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=107">Integrating In-Demand Social Services into Your CTC’s Offerings</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Maria T.  Barker, The Enterprise Foundation; John Garcia
<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=93">Introduction to Microenterprise Development and its Relevance to CTCs</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Bill Edwards, Association for Enterprise Opportunity 
<br><br>
<b>Sustainable Community Technology Business Models for Economic Development </b>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Will Reed, Technology For All – Houston
<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=125">Sustainable Community Technology Business Models for Economic Development in Low-Income Communities</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Jessy Gonzalez, ReliaTech; Paul Lamb, Street Tech; Dr. Will Reed, 
Technology For All; Coretta Alexander, ReliaTech; George Gundrey, CompuMentor
<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=148">Taking Technology Home - From Digital Divide to Digital Development</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Danny Perry, TECH CORPS TEXAS; Nicole Robinson, The Telecom Opportunity Institute (TTOI); Brian Stevens, Houston Information Technology Empowerment Consortium (HITEC); Louis Waters, SimDesk Technologies
<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=137">Unwiring our Communities: Deploying Wireless Technologies to Improve Neighborhoods</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Davis Park, Little Tokyo Service Center Community Development Corporation; Nicole Friedman, Center for Neighborhood Technology – Illinois; Stephen Rockwell, United Way Southeastern Pennsylvania; Nyvia Colon, Madison Park Development Corporation
<br><br>
<b>Web Portals and Community Development
<br>Presented by:</b> Steve Wright, salesforce.com/foundation

]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Spotlight: Lisa J. Servon</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000189.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T10:00:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T06:00:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.189</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T10:00:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"> Lisa J. Servon is Associate Professor of Urban Policy and Associate Director of the Community Development Research Center at the Robert J. Milano Graduate School of Management and Urban Policy, New School University. Professor Servon holds a BA in...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>anonymous</name>
      
      <email>peterm@igc.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Development</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p><table border="0" align="left" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="140" valign="top">
<center><img src="/summer-2004/img/comdevLServonImage.jpg" alt="Lisa Servon">
</center>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
Lisa J. Servon is Associate Professor of Urban Policy and Associate Director of the Community Development Research Center at the <a href="http://www.newschool.edu/milano/">Robert J. Milano Graduate School of Management and Urban Policy</a>, New School University.  Professor Servon holds a BA in Political Anthropology from Bryn Mawr College, an MA in History of Art from the University of Pennsylvania, and a PhD in Urban Planning from the University of California, Berkeley.  She teaches and conducts research in the areas of urban poverty, community development, economic development, and issues of gender and race.  Her presentation at the 2004 CTCNet Conference is on CTCs and youth.
</p><p>
Lisa's specific areas of expertise include microenterprise development, the digital divide, and capacity-building for community-based organizations.  Her work has been funded by the Open Society Institute, the Aspen Institute, the Ford Foundation, and the Fannie Mae Foundation.  She spent much of 2002 as a Visiting Policy Fellow at PolicyLink.  Servon is the author of two books:  <i>Bridging the Digital Divide: Technology, Community, and Public Policy</i> (Blackwell, 2002), and <i>Bootstrap Capital: Microenterprises and the American Poor</i> (Brookings 1999).  She lives in Manhattan with her husband, Alec; her daughter, C.C.; and her dog, Hoover.
</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Staffing for Sustainability: CTCs in Cleveland</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000202.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T09:03:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T05:03:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.202</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T09:03:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">IntroductionOpening a Community Technology Center (CTC) typically requires fewer resources than sustaining its operations over time. &quot;If you build it, they will come&quot; may have worked for Kevin Costner in Field of Dreams, but keeping it going and growing over...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Jassen Tawil</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Organizational Capacity</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p><table border="0" align="right" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1"><tbody><tr><td width="210" valign="top"><center><img src="/summer-2004/img/orgcapmap.jpg" alt="Map of sites with public access to computers in Cleveland"></center></td></tr></tbody></table><b>Introduction</b><br><br>Opening a Community Technology Center (CTC) typically requires fewer resources than sustaining its operations over time.  "If you build it, they will come" may have worked for Kevin Costner in <i>Field of Dreams</i>, but keeping it going and growing over the long-term can be a daunting challenge.  Every community technology center must have a sound sustainability plan, to both satisfy donors and engage in effective planning.  Determining a long-range staffing plan is a key component of overall sustainability. </p><p>In 2003, I was awarded a research grant from the <a href="http://www.cwru.edu/mandelcenter/">Mandel Center for Nonprofit Organizations at Case Western Reserve University</a> to study CTC staffing models.  The Mandel Center, founded in 1984, is one of the nation's first comprehensive nonprofit management programs.  The Center's Research Office offers grants to foster research on nonprofit topics of consequence to the community.  Besides myself, the research team consisted of Professor John Yankey and Ann Lucas, Director of Professional Development Programs.   </p><p><b>Project Background</b></p><p>The research focused on the staffing patterns of Cleveland's Community Technology Centers. The full findings provide CTC decision makers with an overview of their peers' staffing patterns and needs and will hopefully open the door to further inquiry. </p><p>According to <a href="http://www.clevelanddigitalvision.org/">Cleveland Digital Vision</a>, a coalition of organizations working to eliminate the digital divide, the greater Cleveland area has approximately 74 sites where the public can access computer technology and the Internet.  The sites include 24 neighborhood computer centers, 21 recreation centers, and 29 public libraries.</p><p>While time and available resources did not permit visiting each of Cleveland's CTCs, a sample of nine CTCs representative of the range of available programs and services was studied.  The sample included CTCs operated by neighborhood groups, libraries, community development corporations, recreation centers, and churches, and centers with no outside affiliation.  Each sample CTC was visited and surveyed regarding its approach to staffing.  Full participation required following Case Western Reserve University's Institutional Review Board protocol. The findings are summarized below. </p><p><b>Research Findings</b><ul><li>On average, each CTC operates 47 hours each week (Monday-Sunday) with no significant "down time" beyond major holidays. </li><li> 89% have at least one full-time staff person.  Full-time is defined as an employee who works approximately 40 hours per week on either an hourly or salaried basis.</li><li>78% have part-time staff.  Part-time is defined as a regularly employed person working less than 40 hours per week on either an hourly or salaried basis. </li><li>33% currently have volunteer support and 56% had volunteer support in the past.  A volunteer is defined as a person who works at the CTC and is not financially compensated for their time.</li><li>22% currently have subsidized staff and 56% used subsidized staff in the past.  A subsidized staff person is someone who is paid to work at the CTC but not by the CTC itself.  Examples of subsidized staff found in the CTCs studied include: VISTA members, AmeriCorps members, persons doing social work field placements, and work-study students. </li></ul></p><p><b>Staffing for Sustainability</b></p><p>Despite the small sample size, a trend was identified and can serve as the basis for inquiry beyond the predefined scope of the present research.  According to the findings, CTCs used volunteers and subsidized staff in the past more than in the present.  This trend might raise the question: "Why were volunteers and subsidized staff used more in the past than in the present?"  </p><p>One possible answer is that, in the past, volunteers and subsidized staff were relied upon to "build" CTCs—writing curriculum, setting-up computers, building networks, and installing software.  Volunteers and subsidized staff can fill other roles once a CTC is beyond the start-up phase.  The valuable but low to no-cost work that volunteers and subsidized staff perform can help sustain a CTC.  A few examples of sustaining roles played by volunteers and subsidized staff at Cleveland's CTCs include: updating curriculum, offering tutoring, lending expertise (such as an accountant offering e-filing during tax time), conducting marketing and outreach to bring people into a CTC, organizing community meetings, and assessing client satisfaction with programs.  </p><p>Undoubtedly, other roles for volunteers and subsidized staff exist at CTCs.  Developing a strategy to drive a CTC's mission with available resources is critical for long-term sustainability.  The creative use of volunteers and subsidized staff is one way to help sustain a CTC by stretching available funding further while at the same time delivering outcomes that meet community need. <hr><table border="0" align="left" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1"><tbody><tr><td width="140" valign="top"><center><img src="/summer-2004/img/orgcaptawil.jpg" alt="Jassen Tawil"></center></td></tr></tbody></table></p>
<p><div class="bionote"><a href="mailto:jtawil@chnnet.com">Jassen R. Tawil</a> holds a Master of Nonprofit Organizations degree and works at <a href="http://www.chnnet.com/">Cleveland Housing Network</a>'s Community Training and Technology Center under a Technology Opportunities Program grant to provide access and training to underserved Clevelanders.  In 2003, he was awarded a research grant to study the staffing models at Cleveland's CTC.  Cleveland will be the site for the 2005 Annual CTCNet Conference.</div></p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Resources for Organizational Capacity &amp; Leadership Development</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000203.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T09:02:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T05:02:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.203</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T09:02:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Alliance for Nonprofit Management Nonprofit Good Practice Guide: Staff Development &amp; Organizational Capacity (Dorothy A. Johnson Center for Philanthropy &amp; Nonprofit Leadership) CTCNet Leadership Development Institutes Idealist Volunteer Match The CTC VISTA Project CompassPoint Peter F. Drucker Foundation for Nonprofit...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>anonymous</name>
      
      <email>peterm@igc.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Organizational Capacity</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.allianceonline.org/">Alliance for Nonprofit Management</a></p><p>

<a href="http://www.nonprofitbasics.org/"><i>Nonprofit Good Practice Guide: Staff Development & Organizational Capacity</i><br></a>
(Dorothy A. Johnson Center for Philanthropy & Nonprofit Leadership)</p><p>

<a href="http://www.ctcnet.org/ldi/leadinst.htm">CTCNet Leadership Development Institutes</a></p><p>

<a href="http://idealist.org/">Idealist</a></p><p>

<a href="http://www.volunteermatch.org/">Volunteer Match</a></p><p>

<a href="http://www.cpcs.umb.edu/vista">The CTC VISTA Project</a></p><p>

<a href="http://www.compasspoint.org/">CompassPoint</a></p><p>

<a href="http://www.pfdf.org/">Peter F. Drucker Foundation for Nonprofit Management</a></p>]]>
      Additional Resources
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Organizational Capacity and Leadership Track Sessions &amp; Presenters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000183.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T09:01:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T05:01:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.183</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T09:01:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[Funding the Future of Community Technology: funders listen to YOU Presented by: Ken Thompson, The Bill & Melinda Gates Foundation; Jane Meseck, Microsoft Community Affairs; Miguel Garcia, Ford Foundation; Ceil Erickson; The Seattle Foundation; Tessie Guillermo, Community Technology Foundation of...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>anonymous</name>
      
      <email>peterm@igc.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Organizational Capacity</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p><a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=112">Funding the Future of Community Technology: funders listen to YOU
</a><br><b>Presented by:</b> Ken Thompson, The Bill & Melinda Gates Foundation; Jane Meseck, Microsoft Community Affairs; Miguel Garcia, Ford Foundation; Ceil Erickson; The Seattle Foundation; Tessie Guillermo, Community Technology Foundation of California<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=100">The Power of Planning: Technology Planning with Online Tools</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Lindsay Bealko, Npower
<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=136">The Power of Storytelling: Spinning Your Successes & Challenges into (Nonprofit) Gold</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Marissa Martin, CTCNet
<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=99">Staffing for Sustainability</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Jassen Tawil, Mandel Center for Nonprofit Organizations, Case Western Reserve University
<br><br>
<a href="http://ctcnet.org/conf/2004/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=134">Starting Points: Ending Discrimination by Default Against People with Disabilities</a>
<br><b>Presented by:</b> Mary Lester, Alliance for Technology Access (ATA); Russ Holland, Alliance for Technology Access (ATA); Libbie Butler, Alliance for Technology Access; Dave Grass, Northern Illinois Center for Adaptive Technology
]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Spotlight: Mercedes Soto</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000196.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T09:00:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T05:00:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.196</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T09:00:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"> Mercedes Soto currently serves as the Project Director for the innovative Community Technology Center (CTC) Accelerator at the IT Resource Center. The Accelerator is a centralized resource to assist nonprofits that provide technology access and training to low-income community...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>anonymous</name>
      
      <email>peterm@igc.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Organizational Capacity</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p><table border="0" align="left" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="145" valign="top">
<center><img src="/summer-2004/img/orgcapmsoto.jpg" alt="Mercedes Soto">
</center>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
Mercedes Soto currently serves as the Project Director for the innovative Community Technology Center (CTC) Accelerator at the <a href="http://www.itresourcecenter.org/">IT Resource Center</a>. The Accelerator is a centralized resource to assist nonprofits that provide technology access and training to low-income community residents.  Assistance is provided with program development, business planning, staff training, program evaluation, and networking.  Mercedes is a certified teacher with experience in curriculum and staff development and technology in the classroom. Since 1995, she has managed five community technology centers and helped to establish and support more than twenty others.
</p><p>
Mercedes describes her work as follows:
</p><p>
"Through the Accelerator, we've provided hardware, software, cash grants, technical support, networking assistance, staff development, and assistance with evaluation to twenty-two nonprofit organizations in Cook County, IL.  We've helped some organizations start new CTCs, and others enhance and expand services offered through existing CTCs. We've sponsored new CTCNet memberships and membership renewals for all of the organizations and conference registrations for our partner organizations."
</p><p>
Mercedes has served as a member of the national CTCNet Board of Directors and was a founding board member of the its regional chapter, <a href="http://www.luc.edu/curl/prag/ctcnet.htm">CTCNet Chicago</a>. The IT Resource Center is a nonprofit support organization and has been a member of CTCNet since 2000.</p>
]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Youth Engagement in Evaluation and Research</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000204.html" />
    <modified>2005-06-14T08:03:00Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-06-14T04:03:00-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:comtechreview.org,2005:/summer-2004//9.204</id>
    <created>2005-06-14T08:03:00Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">When young people are involved in community research and evaluation, all sides of the equation benefit greatly. Youth engagement bridges the generation gap, provides important information from new perspectives, and builds both skills and community connections for the young people...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Leslie Goodyear and Caroline Bennett</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Research &amp; Evaluation</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/">
      <![CDATA[<p>When young people are involved in community research and evaluation, all sides of the equation benefit greatly.  Youth engagement bridges the generation gap, provides important information from new perspectives, and builds both skills and community connections for the young people involved. Organizations have engaged young people in a diverse array of evaluation and research activities, including community mapping with photography, surveying other young people about attitudes related to drug and alcohol use, and assessing community need for services and advocating for new programs.  Still, there is a vast untapped potential for CTCs to engage the young people they serve in evaluation and research.
</p><p>
There are many good reasons to make an effort at engaging youth in these evaluation and community research projects.  First and foremost, CTCs can provide a great service to young people in their communities by helping them build skills applicable to both academic performance and future employment.  From research, analysis and communication, to databases, software and web development, there are plenty of areas in which young people can gain experience and prowess while providing a service to organizations.  CTCs have the opportunity to offer the opportunity for young people in their communities to develop a proud sense of civic leadership and community participation, which will be of lasting benefit for life.  Through evaluation and research projects with CTCs, young volunteers and their peers enhance their skills and self-esteem, and develop important relationships with professionals, researchers, and other adults.
</p><p>
Young people and organizations can form a mutually-beneficial relationship that promotes positive outcomes for everyone involved.  For CTCs, there are definite rewards to be reaped from engaging young people in community research and program evaluation.  Obviously, incorporating youth perspectives is of great importance to an organization that attempts to serve youth needs.  Often young people can provide information and insight that help CTCs make sure they stay relevant, informed, and connected to their segment of the community.  A healthy amount of diversity and intergenerational respect can be generated by involving young people in research, evaluation, and development.  In sum, CTCs have the power to strengthen local youth and their own organizational culture at the same time.
</p><p>
As with any worthwhile process, there are challenges involved.  Organizations that have engaged young people in research and evaluation projects have found that it involves a major investment of time, training, and support.  It can be difficult for a CTC to arrange its organizational capacity, in terms of funding and staff time, to allow for the special support that young volunteers may need.  In addition, combining rigorous research approaches with youth engagement is challenging and necessitates trusting young people to measure up to your organization's standards.  Another challenge that may arise is ensuring that youth findings and recommendations are treated seriously.  Youth-generated information may challenge established ideas and other findings, and organizations must make a special effort to address youth issues.  Finding the right balance between positive youth development and a CTC's research is by no means a simple task, but there is plenty to make it a rewarding effort.<br>
<hr>
<table border="0" align="left" cellpadding="1" cellspacing="1">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="136" valign="top">
<center><img src="/summer-2004/img/resevalimage.jpg" alt="Leslie Goodyear">
</center>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<div class="bionote"><a href="mailto:lgoodyear@edc.org">Leslie Goodyear</a> is Senior Research Associate for the <a href="http://www2.edc.org/itestlrc/">ITEST</a> (Information Technology Experiences for Students and Teachers) project at <a href="http://www.edc.org/">EDC, Inc.</a>  Her background is in program evaluation and research, with expertise in evaluation methodology, specifically interpretive, mixed-method and participatory-democratic designs for program evaluation and applied research. She holds a B.S. in Psychology from Macalester College, and a Masters and Ph.D. in Human Service Studies and Program Evaluation from Cornell University. Caroline Bennett contributed to this piece.</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>

</feed>