<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<feed version="0.3" xmlns="http://purl.org/atom/ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Fall 2005</title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/" />
  <modified>2005-10-28T04:00:03Z</modified>
  <tagline></tagline>
  <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2007:/fall-2005//16</id>
  <generator url="http://www.movabletype.org/" version="2.661">Movable Type</generator>
  <copyright>Copyright (c) 2005, Editor</copyright>
  <entry>
    <title>ComTechReview and the CTC VISTA Project: Turning Inward and Looking Out Again</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000350.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-28T04:00:03Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-28T00:00:03-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.350</id>
    <created>2005-10-28T04:00:03Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">CTC VISTA Project and CTR staff (2005-2006): Danielle Martin, Shannon McCue, Paul Hansen, Peter Miller, and Saul Baizman The current issue was conceived in the late spring, to be a much smaller special edition, focused on the CTC VISTA Project....</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Editor</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>ComTechReview</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<div class="float_center"><img class="no_float" alt="ctcvista_group.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/ctcvista_group.jpg" width="500" height="267" border="0" /><div class="caption">CTC VISTA Project and CTR staff (2005-2006): Danielle Martin, Shannon McCue, Paul Hansen, Peter Miller, and Saul Baizman</div></div>
<p>The current issue was conceived in the late spring, to be a much smaller special edition, focused on the CTC VISTA Project. It would be something in the nature of a yearbook, with a modest distribution, primarily for the Project's own members and alumni and perhaps of some use as an extended report/presentation/documentation. We're planning to focus on the Project's priority areas in future 2005-06 issues and otherwise giving responsibility over to <em>Review </em>Editorial Advisory Board to help with some serious brainstorming about the future directions of the publication.</p>
<p>Happily, we have extended well beyond those initial modest goals and objectives.&nbsp; Dan Schackman has done an excellent job in focusing on some case studies and the different formats we have used in presenting a perspective on the Project since its inception&mdash;selecting and editing Tech for All Supervisor Doug Caldwell's report on Pete Rodriguez, Jason Crow's narrative on being an VISTA from the VISTA newsletter, Amanda Lasik's weblog entry on the meaning of her work at La Casa Hogar in rural Washington state. He solicited David Rosen's moving tribute and memorial for Larry Syms. He recruited Abby Balazs to report on her MoLLIE/Mobile Learning Lab work in Grand Rapids, Judy Hallman to provide an overview of the work of RTPnet's many VISTAs, Diana Hauer to explore what happened to Teaming for Technology after she left her VISTA work, and Carlos Pedraza to provide a Resource Center perspective.&nbsp; Dan&rsquo;s also contributed a book review on the Corporation for National and Community Service. And we've got Saul Baizman, in his inimitable style, providing exemplary insights on how a wide range of nonprofits can benefit from his work in developing the CTC VISTA Project's information and communication systems. And, to complement our focus on AmeriCorps, Dan sought out complementary International perspectives focusing on the Peace Corps.</p>
<p>That, in itself, would have gone well beyond what we originally conceived.&nbsp; But, in large part thanks to the efforts of new VISTA Assistant Editor Danielle Martin, we've also been able to kick start our planned coverage and resource development in the Project priority areas&mdash;Community Networking, Community Organizing and Development, Technology Assistance to Nonprofits, and Digital Media for Youth.&nbsp; We've done that with her summary reports of what went on at the August Preservice Orientation, supplemented by reports from others who attended, new VISTAs and supervisors alike, including Michael Maranda on community networking and AFCN, Karen Michaelson on TINCAN, Gene Crick on Telecommunity.US and new developments at the FCC, and Tara Kumar on CTCNet's Youth Visions for Stronger Neighborhoods.</p>
<p>There are two other matters of note.&nbsp; First, in response to the devastation following in the wake of Hurricanes Katrina and Rita, both community technology and programs supported by the Corporation for National and Community Service, have played major roles. There's some key coverage about their timely response work here, some from brand new VISTAs Matthew Walker at CTCNet headquarters in DC and Nikki Payne with Technology for All in Houston, who were thrown directly into the midst of CTC response activities and, along with additional stories and resource notes, that make this issue timely and pertinent.</p>
<p><div class="subhead"><em>ComTechReview</em> as Customizable Interactive ICT/Community Media and Technology Curricular Text</div></p>
<p>For the last couple of issues on the inside back cover of the hard copy, we've been running a summary of contents from back issues along with a note &quot;Discounted bulk copies available for classroom use, plus curriculum integration support.&quot;&nbsp; This issue is yet another example of how <em>CTR</em> content can be customized to meet special needs for those of you involved in education and helping people learn more about the field of community media and technology, by rearranging our sections and complementing them with resource sidebars and <em>CTR</em> archive links to material we have published since 2001.</p>
<p>So in turning inward, we trust we are, in fact, reaching back out into the world with some particular useful perspectives, resources, and curriculum on community networking, community organizing and development, technology assistance to nonprofits, and digital media for youth. As always, we welcome your contributions and suggestions.&nbsp; <em>&mdash;pm</em></p>
]]>
      Editor&apos;s Introduction
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The CTC VISTA Project: Looking Back, Looking Ahead</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000348.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-28T04:00:02Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-28T00:00:02-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.348</id>
    <created>2005-10-28T04:00:02Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[As the CTC VISTA Project, in the College of Public and Community Service at the University of Massachusetts, Boston, begins its sixth year partnership with CTCNet and the Corporation for National and Community Service, we&rsquo;d like to reflect on the...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>Daniel Schackman</name>
      <url>www.comtechreview.org</url>
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>ComTechReview</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p>As the CTC VISTA Project, in the College of Public and Community Service at the University of Massachusetts, Boston, begins its sixth year partnership with CTCNet and the Corporation for National and Community Service, we&rsquo;d like to reflect on the fact that to date, 206 individual VISTAs have served at 94 sites in 19 states and the District of Columbia. The Project, one of approximately 100 technology-oriented AmeriCorps programs, continues to be the most sought after national service program in the entire system. This issue of the <em>CTR</em> helps explain why the project has flourished. </p>

<div class="sidebar_right">
  <span class="subhead"><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000349.html">CTC VISTA Project and AmeriCorps Videos and Articles</a></span>
  <ul>
    <li>CTC VISTA Project Videos — A collection by, for, and about CTC VISTAs</li>
    <li><em>ComTechReview</em> archive of articles by, for, and about CTC VISTA Projects and other Ameri*Corps community media and technology programs</li>
  </ul>
</div>

<p>This fall season sees some major changes in project administration.&nbsp; After five years at the helm, Director Peter Miller is stepping back from his leadership role into an advisory capacity while remaining Editor of this journal.&nbsp; Stepping forward as Project Director is former Assistant Director Paul Hansen, who has been with the Project since the spring of 2004 and was previously Operations Manager for the <a href="http://www.dotart.org/">Dorchester Community Center for the Visual Arts</a> in Boston.&nbsp; </p>
<p>In addition to project area support specialists Nettrice Gaskins, Frank Odasz, Ed Schwartz, and Jillaine Smith (see &ldquo;<a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000337.html">The CTC VISTA Project &mdash; Update For Year 6: 2005-'06</a><strong>&rdquo; </strong>in the Spring-Summer 2005 <em>Review</em>), Danielle Martin joins the Project as Curriculum Coordinator and new Assistant Editor of the <em>Review</em> with contributions that are immediately impressive.</p>
<p>As the Project expands to fifty VISTAs serving around the country this year, support for those VISTAs is also expanding. Saul Baizman continues for a second year as a VISTA Leader at Project HQ, working with the Metro Boston contingent and other CTC VISTAs on the East Coast, as well as providing technical support for the national program.&nbsp; Saul is joined by Becky Shuler, supporting our VISTAs in the Midwest, and Mike Denegal, working with folks serving on the West Coast.&nbsp; Both Becky and Mike were CTC VISTAs last year. Becky worked with the Bridges to Digital Excellence Project at the <a href="http://www.cwcconline.com/">Council for World Class Communities</a> in Benton Harbor, Michigan, and Mike worked with the <a href="http://www.sdctc.org/">San Diego Community Technology Coalition</a> and <a href="http://www.ots-sdchc.org/">Occupational Training Services</a> in San Diego, California.&nbsp; Also continuing as a VISTA at Project HQ is Shannon McCue, working with the Community Media and Technology program.</p>
<p>In addition to the contributions of the two VISTA co-editors to this issue, there are five articles by current and recent project VISTAs and two by project supervisors. The VISTA section has additional examples of the impact of the Project &mdash; excerpts from the archives of project reports, newsletters, and VISTA journals, a special memorial tribute, a list and link to project videos and related articles from the <em>CTR</em> archives over the last five years. We trust this gives you a full sense of how Project participants work document our work and some of the most memorable aspects of being a CTC VISTA.</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000384.html">Pete Rodriguez, Technology for All, TX </a><em>by Doug Caldwell</em></li>
  <li>  <em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000385.html">Life as a VISTA: </a></em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000385.html">The VISTA Way</a> <em>by Jason Crow</em></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000386.html">Tribute: Lawrence P. Syms (May 2, 1948 - August 8, 2003)</a> <em>by David Rosen</em></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000387.html">My Work in Rural Washington State</a> <em>by Amanda Lasik</em></li>
</ul>
<HR>
<div class="bionote"><div class="float_left">
<img alt="schackmanreviewimage2small.gif" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/schackmanreviewimage2small.gif" width="64" height="83" border="0" /></div><p><a href="mailto:dcschack@syr.edu">Dan Schackman</a> has been Assistant Editor of the<a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/"> ComTechReview</a> from the Winter 2004-05 issue through this issue, and served as a VISTA Leader for the CTC VISTA Project in 2004-05 and as a VISTA at CTCNet from 2002-04.&nbsp; He is currently a doctoral student in Mass Communications and Graduate Fellow at the S.I. Newhouse School of Public Communications at Syracuse University.</p></div>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Priority Area Presentations at the Pre-service Orientation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000343.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-28T04:00:01Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-28T00:00:01-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.343</id>
    <created>2005-10-28T04:00:01Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[The CTC VISTA Project pre-service orientation (PSO) is a paradox of sorts.&nbsp; The VISTAs are mostly brand new, some never setting foot in their placements before.&nbsp; Yet it is the only chance to meet fellow VISTAs, supervisors and Project staff...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>Danielle Martin</name>
      
      <email>danielle@umb.edu</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>ComTechReview</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.cpcs.umb.edu/vista/PSO_05.doc">The CTC VISTA Project pre-service orientation (PSO)</a> is a paradox of sorts.&nbsp; <a href="http://cpcs.umb.edu/vista/vistas0506.html">The VISTAs</a> are mostly brand new, some never setting foot in their placements before.&nbsp; Yet it is the only chance to meet fellow VISTAs, supervisors and Project staff face-to-face and get answers about the work for the coming year.&nbsp; But how many people can ask questions about an experience they haven&rsquo;t had yet?&nbsp; </p>
<p>In this grand paradoxical experiment, <a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000337.html">four coordinators, tasked to lead the new Project priority areas</a>, were challenged to present an overview of their area of expertise and offer some starting words of advice.&nbsp; This initial mix of experience, naivet&eacute; and energy promised to spur a year of support and resource and curriculum development. The summaries in each section of this issue are a brief attempt to recapitulate three priority area presentations, written by the hand of new VISTA herself in the spirit of PSO paradox.&nbsp; Frank Odasz summarizes some of own his presentation. <a href="http://www.cpcs.umb.edu/vista/vista-videos.html?no_menu">Video excerpts</a> of their presentations are also available.&nbsp; Each summary is complemented with a list of resource links and related articles from the <em>CTR</em> archives.&nbsp; We look forward to the coordinators helping develop their areas as <em>ComTechReview</em> sections in future issues. </p>
<div class="no_float"><img alt="coordinators.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/coordinators.jpg" width="394" height="140" border="0" /></div>
<ul>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000370.html">Nettrice Gaskins:&nbsp; Digital Media for Youth</a></strong></li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000347.html">Frank Odasz: Community Networking</a></strong></li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000374.html">Jillaine Smith:&nbsp; Technology Assistance to Nonprofits</a></strong></li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000364.html">Ed Schwartz: Community Organizing and Development</a></strong></li>
</ul>
<HR>
<p><div class="bionote"><div class="float_left"><img alt="dmartin.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/dmartin.jpg" width="50" height="67" border="0" /></div>
<a href="mailto:danielle.martin@umb.edu">Danielle Martin</a> is a new VISTA tasked to be the priority area curriculum coordinator as well as the Assistant Editor of the Review.&nbsp; Her background is in after-school multimedia programs for youth, instructional design for web-based trainings, and fundraising and development.&nbsp; She was previously the Technology Director at the <a href="http://www.bgcb.org/get_into_clubs/CHARLESTOWN.cfm">Charlestown Boys &amp; Girls Club</a> (MA) <a href="http://www.computerclubhouse.org">Computer Clubhouse</a>.&nbsp; </div></p>]]>
      Focusing the Work of CTC VISTAS
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What is a Community Network? And Why You Should Care!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000347.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-27T04:00:09Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-27T00:00:09-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.347</id>
    <created>2005-10-27T04:00:09Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[A Short Historical Overview Judie Halazon, an early CTC pioneer, offered Free Email from her one computer CTC in Jackson, MT, pop. of 48, starting an rural ecommerce legacy. The term &quot;community networking&quot; originally referred to common community gatherings where...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>Frank Odasz</name>
      
      <email>frank@lone-eagles.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Networking</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<div class="subhead"><p>A Short Historical Overview</p></div>
<div class="float_right" style="width:146px"><img alt="odasz_free.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/odasz_free.jpg" width="146" height="166" border="0" /><div class="caption">Judie Halazon, an early CTC pioneer, offered Free Email from her one computer CTC in Jackson, MT, pop. of 48, starting an rural ecommerce legacy.</div></div>
<p>The term &quot;community networking&quot; originally referred to common community gatherings where everyone gets to know one another. The motivator was making essential connections with those locally who share your interests and understand your needs. In the mid-eighties the term began to be used in reference to people getting to know one another online locally&mdash;with the growing potential for gathering and sharing ideas and resources with anyone, anywhere, anytime.</p>
<p>During this time, &ldquo;online&rdquo; community networks&mdash;Free-Nets&mdash;were formed to provide free dialup Internet access when none was available. Then&mdash;and today&mdash;many use the term &ldquo;community networking&rdquo; in reference to installing Internet infrastructure and nothing more. And many presumed&mdash;and presume today&mdash;that once Internet access has been achieved, the benefits are obvious and come naturally. But the deeper purpose of community networks then, and now, is to create a shared online space for people working together to make good things happen for their communities. </p>
<p><div class="sidebar_right">
  <span class="subhead">More Resources related to the Community Networking priority area:</span>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000352.html">Community Networking - Some Key Sites</a></li>
    <li><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000351.html">Community Networking in the <em>ComTechReview</em> Archives</a></li>
  </ul>
</div>The broadest definition of the term &rdquo;community networking&rdquo; refers to a dedicated group of people working together for a defined purpose, people working together online to realize a shared cause. </p>
<p>Here is one example of a potential shared mission, written for the Association for Community Networking in 1995:</p>
<p>We, the members of AFCN, hold these truths to be self-evident: </p>
<ul>
  <li>that increased connectivity among caring people will build local community social and organizational capacity; </li>
  <li>that resources and effective practices are evolving rapidly and need to be systematically shared between communities; </li>
  <li>that inclusion of members is the source of energy for AFCN and that new methods are needed and we should be consciously evolving innovative inclusive strategies; </li>
  <li>that the pace of technological evolution demands ongoing research and development&mdash;collection and evaluation of what's being done and dissemination of what's found most effective; </li>
  <li>that the social challenges are greater than the technological challenges; </li>
  <li>that we can learn more together than separately; </li>
  <li>that our collaborative effectiveness will increase as we all gain experience and as the tools improve; </li>
  <li>that we must and can invent new ways of inclusive organization.</li>
</ul>
<div class="subhead">Technology Overload and Promising Corporate Foundations</div>
<p>New businesses intent on the commoditization of social interaction are pushing us to join all manner of new communities, from eharmony.com to linkedin.com and more, using all kinds of new technologies&mdash; weblogs or blogs as public web journals, v-logging as video blogs, podcasting via RSS&mdash;and if you&rsquo;re feeling confused, you&rsquo;re not alone. Many adults are lost in this blizzard of accelerating innovation. The U.S. is now somewhere between 15th and 20th in the world for broadband deployment.</p>
<p>Yet, amidst the confusion, what we have is the opportunity to select the specific information flows we want to have in hand &ndash; literally in our hands via handheld devices like Ipods, Blackberries, or Treo hybrid PC/Cell phones &ndash; including multi-media citizen generated broadcasts from any of the growing number of diverse virtual communities. We&rsquo;re seeing an accelerating evolution of innovation unleashed by dropping costs for PCs, software and Internet access. Cellphones are rapidly becoming sophisticated handheld PCs capable of two-way multimedia just-in-time elearning communication.</p>
<p>And corporate developers are laying the foundation for new community networks.</p>
<div class="float_right" style="width:250px"><img alt="odasz_bats.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/odasz_bats.jpg" width="250" height="188" border="0" />
<div class="caption">JJ Sport owner Shane Johnson started by selling one bat on Ebay, and sprouted a 1,000 website affiliates program and expanded into five new product lines in five years.</div>
</div>
<p>EBay promotes the slogan &ldquo;The Power of All of Us&rdquo; referring to the power of many buyers and sellers. By providing a global model for &ldquo;everyman&rsquo;s ecommerce&rdquo; based originally on facilitating online communities for collectors, eBay stands as the most successful model of online community-building in the world (see <a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000261.html">&ldquo;The Power of All of Us: The eBay Lesson for Community Development&rdquo;</a>).</p>
<p>Today eBay, Yahoo, Amazon, Google and other large corporations are beginning to focus on providing localized services&mdash;free collaborative tools (<a href="http://groups.yahoo.com">groups.yahoo.com</a>), free ecommerce web sites (<a href="http://www.tripod.com">tripod.com</a>), free resume-building with local job searches (<a href="http://www.monster.com">monster.com</a>), local searches (<a href="http://www.google.com">google.com</a>), local sales (<a href="http://www.froogle.com">froogle.com</a>), local maps (<a href="http://www.mapquest.com">mapquest.com</a>), local classified ads (<a href="http://craigslist.com">Craig's List</a>),&nbsp; local satellite images and GIS mapping tools (<a href="http://www.earth.google.com">earth.google.com</a>), and even local dating (<a href="http://www.eharmony.com">eharmony.com</a>). </p>
<p>But is a Wal-mart version of local community networking all we have to look forward to? What are the risks? Amid the big business and advancing technology, what role do &ldquo;we the people&rdquo; play? Are we merely consumers or can we participate as producers? Will the telco networks and megacorporations define community for us, or will our communities define these networks to suit community goals instead of corporate goals?&nbsp; Where and how does &ldquo;top-down&rdquo; meet &ldquo;bottom-up.&rdquo; How can the users partner meaningfully with the builders of these networks?</p>
<p>With the push of these megacorporations and their rush for global dominance, somewhere missed is the mission of communities to do for themselves building local collaborative capacity. Certainly there are many positive services these corporations can provide which rural communities in particular cannot create for themselves, such as access to satellite images. What is the ideal role for local citizens to generate their own local content for the benefit of the community? &nbsp;The answers here point to the future of community networking.</p>
<div class="subhead">If we all share what we know, we&rsquo;ll all have access to all our knowledge</div>
<p>With one billion people online, and six billion more due to come online in our lifetime, we share unprecedented opportunities to educate the global population, literally. Our historic opportunity is to work together to learn how best we can keep each other up to the same instant of progress on an ongoing basis&mdash;gathering and disseminating innovations as they occur &mdash; from global sources, while providing knowledge support systems for learning as the need arises.</p>
<p>With each new person who comes online, the potential power of the Internet to benefit others grows. Each new person has the potential to learn from, and to teach anyone, anywhere, anytime. As new skills are acquired, the potential global impact of each individual grows dramatically. As more people learn new collaborative skills, their collective impact becomes exponentially greater.</p>
<div class="float_right" style="width:250px"><img alt="odasz_aust.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/odasz_aust.jpg" width="250" height="188" border="0" />
<div class="caption">Kathryn, an Aboriginal in Yagga Yagga, Australia, explores use of a graphic arts tablet to create aboriginal art, available at <a href="http://www.desart.com.au/">Desart Art Centers</a>.</div>
</div>
<p>Improving technologies for Internet access, such as wireless, are projected to allow free wireless Internet access as the possible norm, a trend already beginning to appear in major population areas. Also appearing are unlimited free multimedia elearning resources, and open source (free) software, all of which are opening minds to the inherent global potential of the power of all of us.</p>
<p>Modular online instruction services already exist, at, for instance, <a href="http://newhorizons.com">New Horizons</a> and <a href="http://ed2go.com">ed2go.com</a>. Skills tutorials complete with assessments, e.g., those at <a href="http://proveit.com">proveit.com</a>, allow anyone to learn online and then demonstrate their skill competencies. While there are lots of free tutorials, lessons, and online courses, there is still a lot of innovation yet to take place in this emerging &quot;marketplace of learning,&quot; particularly regarding peer-mediated learning, both offline and online. Most of us prefer to have someone locally help us learn and this creates major <a href="http://lone-eagles.com/mentoring-mission.htm">opportunities for both volunteerism programs as well as new for-profit local community cooperative services</a>. </p>
<p>  The Internet has unleashed unprecedented entrepreneurial creativity worldwide. Mining the best of these innovations to bring home to empower local communities is a task we will all work together to achieve. Engaging the members of our communities to understand where to go to learn that new knowledge which creates new opportunities is proving to be more and more important to individual and community sustainability.</p>
<p>Our key challenge becomes how to identify the best expertise and greatest wisdom for local and global dissemination&hellip;on an ongoing basis. The potential exists for the wisdom and creative writing and curriculum development of a single individual to impact huge numbers of individuals. Already, some web journals, weblogs or blogs, by such individuals enjoy a readership of thousands. Such blogs are likely to evolve into fast-track elearning pathways designed to impart new skills and capabilities as quickly as possible further leveraging the proliferating array of free web tools.</p>
<div class="float_left" style="width:250px"><img alt="odasz1.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/odasz1.jpg" width="250" height="188" border="0" /><div class="caption">Ron Ridesatthedoor, CEO of sunroadsfarmory.com, presents Montana's first rural Webraising workshop in a one room school in <a href="http://littlerockieszortman.tripod.com">Zortman, MT</a>, pop. 48. </div></div>
<p>Community Networks of geographic place and peer-to-peer social networks have already demonstrated the potential. At <a href="http://wikipedia.org">wikipedia.org</a> over one million topical articles have been donated, creating a robust resource that already rivals the <em>Encyclopedia Britannica</em> as but one example of the future potential of the power of all of us.</p>
<p>Social and economic innovations are merging as new online services in an innovation economy where ideas, resources, and education can be shared without restriction with everyone on earth. These trends present us with the opportunity for the most dramatic positive global change in the history of humankind. The stage is set for everyone to realize their potential as learner and teacher, consumer and producer, all the time.</p>
<HR>
<div class="bionote"><div class="float_left"><img alt="odasz3small2.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/frankhead.jpg" width="114" height="138" border="0" /></div><a href="mailto:frank@lone-eagles.com">Frank Odasz</a> is the Community Networking priority area coordinator for the CTC VISTA Project. He has written extensively for the ComTechReview and is a prolific author whose work can be found at <a href="http://lone-eagles.com">lone-eagles.com</a>, including his summary of <a href="http://lone-eagles.com/ctcvista.htm">&quot;Resources for VISTAS.&quot;</a></div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Community Networking Basics — Some Key Sites</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000352.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-27T04:00:08Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-27T00:00:08-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.352</id>
    <created>2005-10-27T04:00:08Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[The Association for Community Networking (AFCN), www.afcn.org &mdash; note discussion lists and forums, membership services and information including directory of members. Frank Odasz/lone-eagles.com: Frank's articles in CTR archives (see sidebar), lone-eagle VISTA Resources and blog, compilation of Best Community Networking...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>Editor</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Networking</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p>The Association for Community Networking (AFCN), <a href="http://www.afcn.org">www.afcn.org</a> &mdash; note discussion lists and forums, membership services and information including <a href="http://hancock.bev.net/afcn/action.lasso?&-Database=cn_db.fp3&-Layout=afcn_view&-Response=members.lasso&-SortField=country&-SortField=region&afcn=1&-MaxRecords=500&-Search">directory of members</a>. </p>
<p><a href="http://lone-eagles.com/">Frank Odasz/lone-eagles.com</a>: Frank's articles in CTR archives (see sidebar), <a href="http://lone-eagles.com/ctcvista.htm">lone-eagle VISTA Resources</a> and <a href="http://www.cpcs.umb.edu/vista/blog/frank_odasz">blog</a>, compilation of <a href="http://lone-eagles.com/smart.htm">Best Community Networking Resources and Articles</a>, <a href="http://lone-eagles.com/wireless.htm">Community Wireless and Satellite Internet Resources</a><strong>, </strong>and <a href="http://lone-eagles.com/future-proofing.htm">Resource Listings</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.scn.org/tesc-ds/1999-2000/topics/syllabus.html">Civic and Community Networking syllabus</a>, Randy Groves and Doug Schuler, Evergreen State College, Olympia, Washington</p>
<p><a href="http://www.apc.org/english/capacity/training/wireless.shtml">Training Materials: Learn About Wireless Networking</a>, the Association for Progressive Communications (APC)<strong></strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.ntia.doc.gov/otiahome/top/publicationmedia/comm_conn/community_connections_illus.html">Community Connections: Preserving Local Values in the Information Age</a>, Technology Opportunities Program, Department of Commerce, National Telecommunications and Information Administration, (NTIA), September 2000, by Christopher Conte with Judith Sparrow and Don Druker.</p>
<p>New Aboriginal Youth Content Management System at&nbsp;<a href="http://www.deadlyzone.org">deadlyzone.org</a>. Web-authoring and collaboration tools from the <a href="http://www.deadlymob.org">deadlymob.org</a> CTC, an indigenous online community and in Alice Springs, NT (Northern Territory), Australia.</p>
<p>Donnie Morrison's <a href="http://www.work-global.com">Scottish Telework Project</a><strong></strong>has pooled the potential online employee resources of the Outer Hebrides of Scotland to become a leader in e-working by acting as an outsourcing location for customer contact centers.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.tripod.com">Tripod's Free Ecommerce websites</a> and tools.</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Community Networking in the CTR Archives</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000351.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-27T04:00:07Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-27T00:00:07-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.351</id>
    <created>2005-10-27T04:00:07Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Spring-Summer 2005 Community Networking: Movements in the Field and at the Radical Center by Michael Maranda Houston&apos;s Technology for All Wireless Project and the National Municipal Wireless Debate by Will Reed Open Space Austin: April 29-30, 2005 by Frank Odasz...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Editor</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Networking</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p><div class="subhead">Spring-Summer 2005</div></p>
<p><em></em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000318.html">Community Networking: Movements in the Field and at the Radical Center</a> <em>by Michael Maranda </em></em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000330.html">Houston's Technology for All Wireless Project and the National Municipal Wireless Debate</a> <em>by Will Reed </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000317.html">Open Space Austin: April 29-30, 2005</a> <em>by Frank Odasz </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000303.html">Community Networking On The Night Shift, Part Six: The Rise And Fall Of The Ohio Free-Nets</a> <em>by Anne McFarland </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000292.html">Ten Years of the Ohio Community Computing Network (OCCN)</a> <em>by Marsha McDevitt-Stredney</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000327.html">Book Review of <em>Community Practice in the Network Society: Local Action/Global Interaction</em></a> <em>by Daniel Schackman</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000321.html">e-Literacy and Connectivity for Development in India, the Akshaya Approach</a> <em>by Joyojeet Pal and G.R. Kiran</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000322.html">eSeva E-services in Southeast India</a> <em>by Sanjay Jaju</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Winter 2004-2005</div></p>
<p><em></em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000276.html">Community Networking after TOP: Progressive Alliances and a State-by-State Strategy</a> <em>by Michael Maranda</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000259.html">The Champaign-Urbana Community Wireless Network</a> <em>by Sascha Meinrath</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000261.html">The Power of All of Us? &mdash; The eBay Lesson for Community Development</a> <em>by Frank Odasz</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000267.html">CTCNet Delware Valley/Philadelphia Update</a> <em>by Sabra Williams</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000279.html">Broadband &mdash; Why It's Important and Why YOU Should Care</a> <em>by Linda Fowells and Richard Chabr&aacute;n</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000277.html">The New Digital Divide Network</a> <em>by Andy Carvin and Cedar Pruitt</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000283.html">How Wi-Fi Came to El Chaco in the Ecuadorian Rainforest</a> <em>by Klaus Stoll</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000226.html">Hitch Your Wagon to a Star: Reflections on TOP</a>  <em>by Anthony Wilhelm</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Winter-Spring 2004</div></p>
<p><em></em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2004/000166.html">Dispatches from the AFCN</a> <em>by Richard Lowenberg </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2004/000165.html">The Third Age of Community Networking</a> <em>by Andrew Cohill </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2004/000162.html">The Next Wave: Community Information Hubs</a> <em>by Paul Lamb and Vishant Shah </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2004/000163.html">Community Networking on the Night Shift, Part 5: Closing the Books on ACORN &mdash; Well, Almost</a> <em>by Anne McFarland </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2004/000171.html">Growing Demand for Rural Broadband and the Growing Digital Network</a> <em>by R. Terry McGhee</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Summer 2003</div></p>
<p><em></em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2003/000005.html">Creating Our Future: Shaping the Agenda of Community Technology</a> <em>by Kavita Singh and Mary Lester and Gene Crick</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2003/000215.html">AFCN Track Sessions at the 2003 CTCNet conference</a> organized in collaboration with the Alliance for Technology Access and AFCN</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Spring 2003</div></p>
<p><em></em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-2003/000031.html">The Commonwealth Broadband Collaborative and the Premiere of 'First Tuesday'</a> <em>by Peter Miller</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-2003/000035.html">AFCN Update:&nbsp; Community Technology: New Times, New Tactics</a> <em>by Gene Crick</em></p>
<p><em></em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-2003/000037.html">Rodney Williams &ndash; Agent of Change and Content Producer</a>  <em>by Randal Pinkett</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-2003/000038.html">ConnectRichmond: Collecting and Sharing Information to Build a Stronger Community</a> <em>by Nancy Stutts</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-2003/000039.html">KY Consortium Brings Better Access to Deaf/Hard-of-Hearing</a> <em>by Tricia Davis and Ruth McCann</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-2003/000040.html">Common Ground for Alaska, Jamaica, and Rural Idaho</a> <em>by Frank Odasz</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-2003/000041.html">Programming on the Nightshift, Part 6: It Seemed Like a Good Idea at the Time</a> <em>by Anne McFarland</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-2003/000054.html">The Digital City of Parthenay: Social Networks and Civic Nets</a> <em>by Federico Casalegno</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Fall-Winter 2002-2003</div></p>
<p><em></em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000150.html">AFCN Update</a> <em>by Gene Crick</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000105.html">The Rise of the Knowledge Democracy</a> <em>by Andrew Cohill</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000110.html">Transforming Rural Alaska through Wireless Technology in the Schools and Community</a> <em>by Martin Cary</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000112.html">Mapping and Community Organizing in Philadelphia</a> <em>by Eric Hoffman</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000113.html">Edna Jackson, Technology and Community Building: From Staunchest Opponent to Greatest Proponent</a> <em>by Randal Pinkett</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000149.html">Benton Foundation Public Policy Update: Looking to the Future</a> <em>by Norris Dickard</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000120.html">Community Technology in the International Arena</a> <em>by Richard Civille</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000121.html">Community Networking in Post-Soviet Russia</a> <em>by Sergei Stafeev</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000122.html">Penza Association of Refugees and Forced Migrants</a> <em>by Oleg Sharipkov</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000123.html">Municipal and Civic Internet Use in Togliatti</a> <em>by V.V. Efrosinin</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000125.html">Pattern Discussion: Collaborative Design of Community Information Systems</a> <em>by James Zappen</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Winter-Spring 2002</div></p>
<p><em></em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000064.html">AFCN Organizational Update</a> <em>by Andrew Cohill</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000071.html">Thinking Chaordically&mdash;The Future of Communities and Technology</a> <em>by Andrew Cohill</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000069.html">Community Networking on the Night Shift, Part Three: Librarians, Community Networks, and Philosophy Lite</a> <em>by Anne McFarland</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000152.html">Northern New Mexico's Last Mile Technology: Wireless Service!</a> <em>by Judith Pepper</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000058.html">Community Mapping for Neighborhood Knowledge in Los Angeles</a> <em>by Bill Pitkin and Nick Rattray</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000055.html">Running LAPs: On the Local Access Path</a> <em>by Max Gail and Casey Hughes</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000070.html">New Technology Policy and Advocacy Resource from The Children's Partnership</a> <em>by Wendy Lazarus and James Lau</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000065.html">Contentbank.org: Content-Building for and by Local Communities</a> <em>by Laurie Lipper and Francisco Mora</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000056.html">Community Informatics: Current Status and Future Prospects&mdash;Some Thoughts</a> <em>by Michael Gurstein</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000072.html">CTC Collaborations - Building the Timothy Smith Network in Boston</a> <em>by Marc Osten</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000067.html">Stopping in at TOP</a> <em>by Phil Shapiro</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000080.html">A Mixed Picture&mdash;Telecom Policy Update and Analysis</a> <em>by Ryan Turner, plus <a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000079.html">Addendum to A Mixed Picture</a> </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000074.html">Closing The Resource Gap: 1-2-3 Advocacy to Improve Illinois Communities through Telecommunications, in Three Stages of Regulatory Competition, 1997-2001</a> <em>by Layton Olson</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000068.html">Buenos Aires, Montreal, and Seattle: Civic Unrest and Civic Intelligence</a> <em>by Doug Schuler</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000077.html">On the World Social Forum in Porto Alegre, Brazil</a> <em>by Scott Robinson</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Summer-Fall 2001</div></p>
<p><em></em><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-fall-2001/000133.html">The Association for Community Networking</a> <em>by Andrew Cohill</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-fall-2001/000089.html">Planning for Local Community Internet Awareness Initiatives</a> <em>by Frank Odasz</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-fall-2001/000090.html">The New Gold Rush&mdash;Mining Raw Human Potential Using Free Web Tools</a> <em>by Frank Odasz</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-fall-2001/000136.html">The Ars Portalis Project</a> <em>by Richard Civille</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-fall-2001/000092.html">Community Networking on the Night Shift, Part Two: in which a Community Organizer Tries to Be a Techie</a> <em>by Anne McFarland</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-fall-2001/000134.html">Stopping by Benton</a> <em>by Phil Shapiro</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-fall-2001/000158.html">Public Policy and Related References and Resources</a> </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-fall-2001/000098.html">Digital Empowerment Programs for the Underserved</a> <em>by Cory Smith</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-fall-2001/000144.html">International Community Technology Development Since Barcelona</a> <em>by Richard Lowenberg and Steve Ronan and Steve Cisler</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-fall-2001/000157.html">The Community Information Corps at the University of Michigan School of Information</a> <em>by Paul Resnick</em></p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Democratic Vistas: Community Networking as the Practical Work of Regional and Local Organizing</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000361.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-27T04:00:06Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-27T00:00:06-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.361</id>
    <created>2005-10-27T04:00:06Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[ There are metaphors and frames without which we would be at a loss to convey the profundity of change in our conception of the world and our possible futures.&nbsp; Such archetypal ideas have been called conceptual primitives:&nbsp; they involve...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Maranda</name>
      
      <email>mmaranda@afcn.org</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Networking</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<div class="float_right" style="border-bottom:none;"><img alt="AFCNlogo.gif" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/AFCNlogo.gif" width="133" height="133" border="0" /></div>
<p>There are metaphors and frames without which we would be at a loss to convey the profundity of change in our conception of the world and our possible futures.&nbsp; Such archetypal ideas have been called conceptual primitives:&nbsp; they involve words that are overloaded with meaning and can&rsquo;t be limited within particular definitional forms, finding application in diverse contexts and communities of discourse.</p>
<p>Doubly so when we combine <em>Community </em>and<em> Networking.</em></p>
<p>The current invitation to practice community networking offers a timely return to the relevance of <em>place</em> alongside recent invitations centered on <em>process</em>. The achievements of RTPnet and TINCAN that Judy Hallman and Karen Michaelson write about in this issue clearly grow out of and contribute back into the life and culture of Raleigh-Durham, NC, and Spokane, Washington.</p>
<p>In the United States, policy folk speak of the &ldquo;States as Policy Laboratories&rdquo; where policies can and should be field-tested and, hopefully, the successful models replicated elsewhere.&nbsp; The October <a href="http://www.ruraltelecon.org">Rural TeleCon (RTC)</a> conference in Lexington, Kentucky emphasized this view with respect to U.S. broadband policy.&nbsp; Admittedly, our view of politics may have grown a little more cynical and polarized.&nbsp; Rather than policy laboratories, it is easy to see battlegrounds, especially as we gird ourselves for the reconsideration of national telecommunications and media policy soon to come before Congress.</p>
<p>So do let us take advantage of the smaller arenas where it is easier to view politics as a grand experiment where we all play a significant part.&nbsp; Let the republic be a question, and let us take part in ensuring appropriate method and safeguards in answer to the pressing issues of the day with a commitment to the long view.&nbsp; </p>
<p>We each have a role and stake in governance. In the Community Information and Communications Technology sector, we are uniquely positioned to promote an inclusive and extensive vision that is, at heart, political in the grand and experimental sense of civic engagement and that evokes those struggles that inspired the democratic vistas once painted on the world stage.&nbsp; </p>
<p>In Illinois, <a href="http://www.ctcnetchicago.org/">we</a> call for &quot;Digital Literacy, Access, and Equity&quot; as we create <a href="http://www.ilctc.org/">the Illinois Community Technology Coalition</a>.&nbsp; We are experimenting with a model of &ldquo;civic engagement and improving the quality of life by working together,&rdquo; exploring how we can be of meaningful resource to each other in a network.&nbsp; We&rsquo;ve been inspired by colleagues in Ohio, California and Minnesota, to name just a few.&nbsp; And like Ohio and elsewhere, we&rsquo;ve placed community networking at the center of our effort to organize stakeholders around a bold vision.&nbsp; </p>
<p>These regional developments are our field&rsquo;s most vital response to the challenges of our day.&nbsp; Together we participate in a national&mdash;and moreover, worldwide&mdash;movement.&nbsp; Thankfully there are now networks of practice that connect us with national organizations promoting our philosophy.&nbsp; But the complex web of governance and jurisdiction involves local and state as well as national, and in some cases international, bodies. It turns out that these national organizations we have formed to serve our collective interests (AFCN, CTCNet, RTC, etc.) are greatly dependent upon strong regional capacity if they are to accomplish what we&rsquo;ve asked of them. </p>
<p>National level organizations frequently are organized around an issue or around a field of practice.&nbsp; There is nothing unusual in this.&nbsp; What is significant is that local and regional organizing is more effectively undertaken on another basis:&nbsp; the engagement of diverse stakeholders in the widest common frame, rather than a community of practice or vested interest in particular issues. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000308.html">In the last issue of the <em>CTR</em>, Angela Stuber</a>, Executive Director of the Ohio Community Computing Network and President of the Board of CTCNet, described a shift in this direction for the Ohio model.&nbsp; The new mission statement extends beyond CTCs to community technology services and programs.&nbsp; Likewise, the &quot;Digital Vision&quot; proclaimed in Cleveland at the CTCNet national conference entails a process of engaging stakeholders in a meaningful way that crosses the categories that orient us within our field.</p>
<p>In Illinois&mdash;in our expression of a grand and inclusive vision to bring together individuals and organizations concerned with promoting digital literacy, access and equity&mdash;we are actively reaching out to diverse communities of practice. We believe that community information and communications technologies have application in all spheres of our common life; they require and enable the opportunity to engage us all in civic life and processes of governance.&nbsp; </p>
<p>The process of organizing on this regional basis is not easy.&nbsp; It is colored by the language and place from which one starts.&nbsp; How it unfolds where you undertake this effort will be shaped by local concerns and the stakeholders you can convene, and there is as much messiness as there is beauty in this very human interaction. Perhaps this meets Garth Graham's call to <a href="http://ci-journal.net/viewarticle.php?id=88&layout=html">&quot;Community Networking as Radical Practice&quot;</a> in the recent <em>Journal of Community Informatics </em>article where he otherwise questions our status as a movement. By shifting to a radical local-global practice in a process of continual organizing, we return to our roots.&nbsp; We can&rsquo;t despair the death of community networking if this has been a shedding of surface features.&nbsp; If Garth is right, we&rsquo;re much deeper than a movement.&nbsp; But this will take significant movement on our part, and not just a little storytelling.&nbsp; </p>
<p>Tell your story in your community, involving all members in the process.&nbsp; As your stories unfold, share them with us.&nbsp; If our states and local communities are to be the locus of social experiment, with our field in a facilitating role, we need not do so in isolation nor in competition with each other&mdash;though a little local pride won&rsquo;t hurt and may very well be necessary.</p>
<p><div class="subhead">Common Disaster&mdash;and Opportunity</div></p>
<p>Community networking offers a profoundly new way of looking at the world, its forms and language still unfolding.&nbsp; We&rsquo;re only just catching up with the dynamic nature of the world and the potential for diversity in social organization and yet we&rsquo;re equally prone to abandon our progress for a false sense of security.</p>
<p>The Gulf storms of 2005 made the case for distributed capacity and expertise to deploy networks throughout society&mdash;in business and government as well as community. Mobilization for everything needed, from direct help to communications network deployment to database development and support, presents a challenge. We have the opportunity to redefine &quot;critical infrastructure&quot; to include human systems and coordination of volunteer resources and talents.&nbsp; </p>
<p>There are numerous stories of responses to these natural disasters that are cases in point.&nbsp; In this <em>CTR</em> issue, several authors share these stories: Matt Walker on CTC efforts, Gene Crick on TeleCommunity.US crisis management in Austin, Nichole Payne's account of Tech for All's building the Astrodome Community Technology center in Houston, and Nicole Friedman on Chicago's Center for Neighborhood Technology Wireless Community Network's volunteer efforts in Louisiana highlight some exemplary work in this regard.</p>
<HR>
<p><div class="bionote"><div class="float_left"><img alt="marandaimage1small.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/marandaimage1small.jpg" width="150" height="146" border="0" /></div>
  <p><a href="mailto:mmaranda@afcn.org">Michael Maranda</a> is the President of the <a href="mailto:www.afcn.org">Association For Community Networking</a> and Director of <a href="http://www.ctcnetchicago.org/">CTCNet Chicago</a> as well as Co-Chair of the <a href="http://www.ilctc.org/">Illinois Community Technology Coalition</a>.</p>
  <p>&nbsp;</p>
  <p>&nbsp;</p>
</div></p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Community Networks: The Future Has Arrived</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000346.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-27T04:00:05Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-27T00:00:05-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.346</id>
    <created>2005-10-27T04:00:05Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[After a few years' declining support and growth, time are changing for community technology and networking. &nbsp;Recent events have dramatically demonstrated the need and importance of community-centered telecommunications capability, spurring local technology advocates to think "outside the coffin" and address...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>Gene Crick</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Networking</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p>After a few years' declining support and growth, time are changing for community technology and networking. &nbsp;Recent events have dramatically demonstrated the need and importance of community-centered telecommunications capability, spurring local technology advocates to think "outside the coffin" and address today's challenges with renewed optimism, energy, and purpose.&nbsp; Though a "Perfect Community Technology Network" doesn't exist and never will, strong examples are emerging, with lessons to benefit all who share experience and information.</p>
<p><div class="sidebar_right"><strong>Check out Gene Crick's notes on<br><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000394.html">TechTalk: Dropped Into Deep Drupal – a NOC, NOC story</a>.</strong></div>For instance, at <a href="http://www.tcrc.net">TeleCommunity Resource Center (TCRC.net)</a> we're working on new community programs and a highly automated community information system (based primarily on open source technology) at <a href="http://www.main.org">Metropolitan Austin Interactive Network (MAIN.org)</a> to streamline our own services and offer simplified models for other community networks (CNs), especially those with less technology capacity than "geek-intensive" Austin.&nbsp; But this goal of new resources, new features, and new directions isn't possible for any CN working in isolation.&nbsp; So we are asking everyone we know for ideas, and sharing our own experiences, good and bad, with anyone who asks.&nbsp; Here are three current project examples. </p>
<div class="subhead">Information Sharing:&nbsp; Telecommunity.US/Crisis Management</div>
<p><a href="http://www.Telecommunity.US">www.Telecommunity.US</a> is a national collaborative initiative just launched to help build greater information sharing and awareness among communities using telecommunications for local benefit.&nbsp; It is simply a cooperative information forum, <em>not</em> another organization competing for publicity and funding. Partner groups during early development include the TeleCommunity Resource Center and Metropolitan Austin Interactive Network, the <a href="http://www.afcn.org">Association for Community Networking (AFCN)</a>, <a href="http://www.techforall.org/">Technology For All</a>, the <a href="http://www.tispa.org/">Texas ISP Association</a>, and <a href="http://www.salsa.net">SalsaNet</a>.&nbsp; Other groups are now joining &ndash; we hope you'll participate as well.&nbsp; No obligation beyond sharing ideas and knowledge.</p> 

<p>The first Telecommunity.US effort was decided entirely by Mother Nature.&nbsp; When Hurricanes Katrina and Rita hit us in Louisiana and Texas, the deplorable state of disaster preparedness and emergency management quickly became obvious.&nbsp; As hundreds of thousands evacuated hurricane-devastated areas, official plans often lapsed into chaos of poor communication and misdirected (or entirely missing) relief resources.&nbsp; But due largely to inspiring efforts of community volunteers, a near-calamity was gradually brought under control.&nbsp; Blunders of government and high-profile charities were balanced by heartening stories of local responders like Houston's Will Reed, whose tireless work has become almost legendary among those of us working on relief projects.</p>
<p>Thus Telecommunity.US was forced to get off the drawing board and go to work.&nbsp; We hurriedly created a local/regional information and assistance program for communication among relief efforts for Katrina, Rita and future crises.&nbsp; In the event of a crisis, our mission is to assist with use of Internet information-sharing technology to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>provide news, information, and vital resources to identify and obtain support needed by survivors;</li>
  <li>help keep disaster relief groups and workers aware of all relevant activities, resources, and information;</li>
  <li>describe clear and effective ways volunteers can help.</li>
</ul>
<p>In normal times our goals focus on helping communities:</p>
<ul>
  <li>view examples and develop local disaster-preparedness/crisis management plans incorporating available resources, relevant services and reliable rapid contact information;</li>
  <li>create functional, comprehensive local public health, safety and crisis websites;</li>
  <li>disseminate useful guidelines for family preparedness and emergency procedures and to develop "neighborhood preparedness" crisis programs;</li>
  <li>create functional, comprehensive model websites for local public health, safety and crisis; </li>
  <li>build information/assistance collaborations within cities, regions, and beyond.</li>
</ul>
<p>We invite comments, suggestions, information and help in developing this community-based communications resource for crisis preparation and response.&nbsp; Other examples are appreciated.</p>
<div class="subhead">Voices on Policy:&nbsp; Community Technology Speaks to the FCC</div>
<p>Increasingly, community Internet advocates express concern that current national policy is not bringing information technology access and opportunities to every American.&nbsp; Affordable choices for broadband and advanced telecommunications services are still not available to people in many parts of the country, especially in rural and less affluent urban areas. &nbsp;Locally-based Internet companies are being driven out of business by giant corporations using tactics that some claim are unethical, if not illegal. &nbsp;Important educational and public interest programs are being slashed.&nbsp; Overall, the current political climate has not been favorable for community technology.</p>
<p>Many of us worry that government telecom policymakers are not receiving an accurate, balanced picture.&nbsp; We fear they are overly influenced by too much input from dominant telecom providers and too little from consumers and communities who lack the resources to rival heavily funded industry lobbies. &nbsp;But recent developments can provide another channel Americans can use to make our voices heard by telecom policymakers.</p>
<p>The TeleCommunity Resource Center has been appointed by FCC Chairman Martin as a member organization of the FCC Consumer Advisory Committee.&nbsp; I have been appointed Chairman of their Working Group on Rural and Underserved Broadband Access. These two appointments offer an important official method for communities to submit our views, desires, and comments on telecom issues affected by policy decisions of the FCC. &nbsp;Though the FCC may not take the actions requested in our comments, at least they will formally read and review them.</p>
<p>With the assistance and support of the <a href="http://www.afcn.org">Association for Community Networking</a> and <a href="http://www.consumersunion.org">Consumers Union</a>, the TCRC has created <a href="http://www.tcrc.net/fcccomments.asp">a website for public input</a>, a nonprofit, nonpartisan public interest arena for anyone interested in telecommunications, regardless of viewpoint or affiliation. &nbsp;TCRC is collecting, summarizing, and submitting comments to the FCC Consumer Advisory Committee, Chairman and officials.&nbsp; Comments will be maintained online for all interested viewers, including public policymakers.&nbsp; Commenters can specify whether their names are shown or withheld.</p>
<p>These comments can provide the FCC with the widest possible input from all segments of the American public.&nbsp; But it will only make a difference if enough comments are offered. So we need your ideas and assistance&mdash;and your suggestions for improving the site and the services it offers.</p>
<div class="subhead">Community Stories: &nbsp;"Write On!" Local Authors Project</div>
  <p>Mayor Will Wynn of Austin is strongly committed to literacy, the arts, and broader community understanding.&nbsp; His goals prompted the newly created <a href="http://www.writeonaustin.org">"Write On, Austin!"</a> online project to encourage veteran and aspiring writers to submit brief stories on Austin life. &nbsp;Primary partners are the City of Austin, Austin Public Library, University of Texas Humanities Institute, and MAIN.Noting positive benefits of building local literary strength as well as improving intra-community awareness and involvement, other cities are looking to develop similar projects.&nbsp; Within days of Austin's September 27 debut, plans began for <em>Write On! San Antonio</em> and others are under discussion.&nbsp; These local writing projects will be cross-linked, sharing common resources like tools, organizations, and educational opportunities for writers.&nbsp; As with other project models, TCRC will provide additional details, templates, and assistance to anyone interested.&nbsp; We appreciate any suggestions for improvement and information about similar projects elsewhere. </p>

<div class="subhead">Bottom Line</div>
   <p>Community technology has renewed opportunity for service and growth.&nbsp; Among our various project we have experience and information to meet most of the challenges we face.&nbsp; Using our own tools to share collective knowledge and support each other can make the coming years our best ever.</p>
<HR>   
<div class="bionote"><div class="float_left"><img alt="genepublicity.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/genepublicity.jpg" width="114" height="155" border="0" class="float_left" /><a href="mailto:gcrick@main.org">Gene Crick</a> is Executive Director of the TeleCommunity Resource Center, member of the FCC Consumer Advisory Committee, Chair of their Working Group on Rural and Underserved Broadband Access, and past President of the Association for Community Networking.</div></div>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>TechTalk: Dropped Into Deep Drupal – a NOC, NOC story</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000394.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-27T04:00:04Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-27T00:00:04-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.394</id>
    <created>2005-10-27T04:00:04Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[For more than a decade our MAIN/TCRC community Network Operating Center (NOC) has been running smoothly, with Unix, Linux, NT, and Apple servers supporting both our R&amp;D and free nonprofit organization hosting services.&nbsp; But even though it wasn&rsquo;t &ldquo;broken,&rdquo; we...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>Gene Crick</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Networking</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p>For more than a decade our <a href="http://www.main.org/">MAIN</a>/TCRC community Network Operating Center (NOC) has been running smoothly, with Unix, Linux, NT, and Apple servers supporting both our R&amp;D and free nonprofit organization hosting services.&nbsp; But even though it wasn&rsquo;t &ldquo;broken,&rdquo; we recently decided to &ldquo;fix it&rdquo; anyway.&nbsp; Want to guess how that turned out?&nbsp; </p>
<p><div class="sidebar_right"><span class="subhead">Read Crick's full article:</span><br><strong><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000346.html">Community Networks: The Future Has Arrived</a></strong></div>Our Revered Online Systems Director noticed we were due a major overhaul to increase power, user features, and operating efficiency.&nbsp; Key changes were upgrading to newest Linux OS on our primary server and installing later Drupal/Civicspace content management software releases.</p>
<p><strong>Lesson One:</strong>&nbsp; We didn&rsquo;t realize multi-generation upgrades, like changing Red Hat from version 7 to version 12, are not necessarily compatible with all other server software.&nbsp; (Visualize a server without DNS and email software.&nbsp; Now wipe away your tears.) </p>
<p>Our next major upgrades (currently scheduled for October, 2041) will be on our mirror site first.&nbsp; When reviews are good, then we&rsquo;ll bring the show into town. &nbsp;[Tip: Find a sister CN with similar servers; we&rsquo;re cross-mirroring with <a href="http://www.salsa.net">Salsa.net</a> in San Antonio.]</p>
<p><strong>Lesson Two:</strong>&nbsp; Try <em>really, really </em>hard not to begin community support server overhaul just before two hurricanes strike.&nbsp; I can&rsquo;t emphasize this one enough; typing underwater became a total pain.&nbsp; Check first with the weather service, religious leaders, psychic hotlines, and your granny&rsquo;s knee.</p>
<p>But all ended well.&nbsp; Revered Director was right; the NOC is running better than ever. </p>
<p>Note:&nbsp; Though tested operations models help, running a CN server is still demanding, even with outside R&amp;D.&nbsp; Security and spam protection alone have become so difficult that many smaller nonprofit and commercial ISPs are quitting, unable to justify the overhead.&nbsp; So while we believe ICT networks are important, not every community has sufficient local technology capacity to run its own NOC.&nbsp; We&rsquo;ve started testing free hosting for a few smaller towns and would like to hear from any other CNs doing the same. </p>
<HR>   
<div class="bionote"><div class="float_left"><img alt="genepublicity.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/genepublicity.jpg" width="114" height="155" border="0" class="float_left" /><a href="mailto:gcrick@main.org">Gene Crick</a> is Executive Director of the TeleCommunity Resource Center, member of the FCC Consumer Advisory Committee, Chair of their Working Group on Rural and Underserved Broadband Access, and past President of the Association for Community Networking.</div></div>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>CTC VISTAs Strengthen RTPnet</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000362.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-27T04:00:03Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-27T00:00:03-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.362</id>
    <created>2005-10-27T04:00:03Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"> RTPnet, previously known as Triangle Free-Net and so named for the Research Triangle Park area between Raleigh, Durham and Chapel Hill, is a volunteer-driven, 501(c)3 nonprofit community network dedicated to helping North Carolina nonprofit organizations leverage Internet tools to...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Judy Hallman</name>
      
      <email>hallman@email.unc.edu</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Networking</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p><div class="float_right"><img alt="rtpnet logo" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/rtpnetlogo.jpg" width="150" height="101" border="0" /></div>
<a href="http://www.rtpnet.org">RTPnet</a>, previously known as Triangle Free-Net and so named for the Research Triangle Park area between Raleigh, Durham and Chapel Hill, is a volunteer-driven, 501(c)3 nonprofit community network dedicated to helping North Carolina nonprofit organizations leverage Internet tools to promote and support their missions.</p>
<p>RTPnet offers annual <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/hosting/">fee-based memberships</a> to North Carolina nonprofits and CTCs in the southeast. Member benefits include web hosting, e-mail list management (using Mailman as its list serve software), and discounts for RTPnet-sponsored training and events, including an annual statewide conference on bridging the digital divide. AmeriCorps*VISTAs have supported RTPnet community technology projects since the CTC VISTA Project was established as a national effort. </p>
<div class="float_left" style="width:250px"><img alt="chad_morgan.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/chad_morgan.jpg" width="250" height="207" border="0" /><div class="caption">CLICK coordinator Chad Custer is helping 6th grader Morgan Timberlake with her Travel Project (Pictures from The Herald-Sun)</div></div>
<p>VISTA projects allow host organizations to develop and expand programs and services with side benefits that strengthen the host organization. The CTC VISTA Project has strengthened RTPnet and our member network through fostering collaborations, providing a foundation for increased financial support, contributing to an increased understanding of digital divide issues, and helping us attract and support additional volunteers.</p>
<p><strong>Collaboration:</strong> The process of defining VISTA projects, finding funding, and supervising VISTA work has brought together a variety of organizations and resources. For example: </p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.unitedwaytriangle.org">Triangle United Way</a> and RTPnet co-sponsored VISTAs, Damita Chambers and Vahid Nourani in 2004-05. RTPnet recruited them and had financial responsibility; Triangle United Way provided office space and supervision. Damita and Vahid's work expanded and solidified cooperation between local nonprofit technology assistance providers and well as strengthened the nonprofits they worked with directly.</li>
  <li>Duke University and RTPnet collaborated to establish <a href="http://www.duke.edu/web/isis/click/">CLICK</a>, Creating Literacy in Computer Knowledge. A Duke junior, Matt Lipsky, was developing an after-school program to help 6th graders pass the North Carolina computer competency test. Through the CTC VISTA project, RTPnet recruited Douglas Dumont, a Duke graduate, to work full time assisting Matt in developing CLICK. Duke's Information Science + Information Studies provided the funding for the VISTA position, the office space and supervision; RTPnet did the recruiting and provided additional support through developing ties with a similar project at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. We were fortunate to find a second VISTA, Chad Custer, to expand CLICK while continuing it for a second year. </li>
  <li>Area VISTAs themselves can be a catalyst for regional collaboration. VISTAs working in different organizations get to know each other during preservice orientation and later help forge connections. Ben Pratt (Durham Literacy Center) and Chad Custer (RTPnet) shared an apartment; Luke Reinke (Durham Literacy Center) and Douglas Dumont (RTPnet) shared ideas as they worked in parallel middle school settings to develop after-school computer literacy programs; Martha Moore shared some of the family literacy ideas from the Durham Literacy Center with the students and volunteers at her center; ideas for recycling computers were shared among all the VISTAs in the area.&nbsp; VISTA involvement in the RTPnet annual conferences built on and reinforced regional collaboration.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Increased financial support:</strong> RTPnet membership fees provide a base of seed money for the $3,000-$4,000 in funding needed for VISTA positions. When we start a VISTA project, we have the money in the bank to pay for it. In many cases, the VISTA project generates additional funds. As noted, the two VISTAs for CLICK were funded entirely by Duke. In addition:</p>
<ul><div class="float_right" style="width:300px"><img alt="gena marsha.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/gena+marsha.jpg" width="300" height="262" border="0" /><div class="caption">Eugena Harrington with CNS program officer Marsha Colbert.</div></div>
  <li>Our first tech support VISTA, Eugena Harrington (2001-02) did such a good job assisting 20 community technology centers in Orange, Durham, and Wake counties and helping schools in the area that RTPnet received a small grant from a local church toward the expenses for another VISTA to continue this work. </li>
  <li>Two VISTAs, Ella Holden (2002-04) and Kimmora McKinnie (2001-02), were funded jointly by the Riley Hill Community Technology Center and RTPnet; Riley Hill CTC paid the program fees, while RTPnet covered CTCNet conference and other costs. </li>
  <li>Another VISTA, Shirlene Rogers (2001-03), was funded by a grant from Verizon. </li>
</ul>
<p>In addition, the VISTAs' good work on projects enhances RTPnet's ability to attract members and donations.</p>
<p> <strong>Increased understanding of digital divide issues:</strong><div class="sidebar_right"><strong>Check out Judy Hallman's RTPnet <br>
  Adult Basic Computer Ed Handouts <a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000373.html">here</a>.</strong></div><a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/tact/jobinfo/vista1.html"> Martha Moore's project</a> (2001-04) at the Birchwood Learning Center in Durham opened the eyes of many RTPnet associates to the difficulties associated with running a learning center in a low-income neighborhood plagued with drugs, alcohol, and violence. The team of leaders who helped initiate this project and were supposed to coordinate it disappeared, Martha nonetheless, with guidance, made good progress working with adults. She found that she could actually increase attendance in evening classes by charging a small monthly fee, paid in advance, since the participants had then made a commitment and were more likely to attend classes. But it continued to be difficult to get adults to come to the center. And then the police requested that classes be moved from evening to daytime after a shooting near the center. Gradually, Martha's work focused more on special projects and the after-school program developed in partnership with the John Avery Boys and Girls Club.&nbsp; For the last two years, Martha was the only staff person there. </p>
<p><strong>More volunteers:</strong> As people learn about our VISTA programs, they realize that they can also contribute as volunteers. Increased volunteerism is both a blessing and a challenge. With the help of Shirlene Rogers (2001-03), we created databases of CTCs and of volunteer skills and availability. Our latest effort, <a href="http://www.techlinkup.org/">Tech LinkUp</a>, has been designed to help connect volunteers, sponsors, and businesses with community organizations, and to help connect community organizations with one another for mutual support. </p>
<p><div class="subhead">RTPnet VISTA Projects</div></p>
<div class="float_right" style="width:250px"><img alt="moore03sep26.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/moore03sep26.jpg" width="250" height="161" border="0" /><div class="caption">Martha Ann Moore displays her community leadership award, flanked by Stephen Quinn (left) and John Zoltner (right) of CTCNet's DC staff.</div></div>
<p>CTC VISTAs sponsored by RTPnet have made significant contributions to efforts to bridge North Carolina's digital divide.&nbsp; To note more about their work:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Martha Ann Moore</strong>'s achievements were acknowledged by <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/rtpnet/news/moore03sep.html">her selection for a Technology to Empower Communities (TEC) Champion Award</a> for Outstanding Community Technology Leaders. In addition, Martha was the recipient of a <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/awards/nominees.html">2004 Community Technology Award</a>, presented at the <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/rtpnet/rtpconf04/">5th Annual RTPnet Conference</a>. </li>
  <li><strong>Eugena Harrington</strong> &mdash; it is not surprising grants came in to continue support for <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/tact/jobinfo/vista2.html">Gena's project</a>. As an acknowledgement from one of Gena's school centers put it:&nbsp; &quot;Gena the great: Thank you for sending Gena along. She has been brilliant! Got laptop fixed up with ethernet and modem. Has volunteered to set-up ten computers donated to our school. She is kind and tenacious&hellip; She has given hours and great kindness and support. Gena is a generous genie, and a gem of genius!&quot; </li>
  <li><strong>Kimmora McKinnie</strong> (2001-02): <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/tact/jobinfo/vista3.html">Kimmora's project</a> was to provide technical support and training support to the Eastern Wake CTC in the Riley Hill Family Life Center. Kimmora recruited adult students (ages 19 to 82), taught introductory computer courses, and trained community volunteers to teach the courses. She initiated an after-school program, with students recruited through the East Wake Middle School guidance department, and recruited community volunteers to assist her work with the middle school students. </li>
  <li><strong>Ella Holden</strong> (2002-04): <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/tact/jobinfo/vista5.html">Ella's project</a> provided technical support and training for the Riley Hill CTC. Ella taught classes for adults and worked with youth in the after-school program, continuing and expanding the programs started by Kimmora. She also expanded community involvement in the center and developed a computer repair course. </li>
  <li><strong>Shirlene Rogers</strong> (2001-03): <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/tact/jobinfo/vista4.html">Shirl's project</a>, along with the volunteer database she developed that paved the way for Tech LinkUp, was to assist the President of the CTCNet board of directors, Erroll Reese in Durham, with program development and capacity building and included research, statistical analyses, reports, speeches, and PowerPoint presentations promoting CTCNet at several major conferences. </li>
  <li><strong>Douglas Dumont</strong> (2002-03): <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/tact/jobinfo/vista6.html">Douglas' after-shool CLICK project</a>, developed at <a href="http://www.wfl.dpsnc.net/lt/rherr/school.nsf/">Rogers Herr Middle School</a> in Durham, also involved creating a template for replicating the program in North Carolina and nationwide. The <a href="http://www.duke.edu/web/isis/click/curriculum.html">curriculum</a>, lesson plans and teaching modules, oriented toward 6th graders, were presented at the <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/rtpnet/rtpconf03">RTPnet 2003 conference</a> and at the CTCNet 2003 conference, as part of the session <a href="http://www.ctcnet.org/conf/2003/at_conference/program_detail.asp?SessionID=39">CTCs &amp; Local Schools</a>, and are freely available. </li>
  <li><div class="float_right" style="width:150px"><img alt="vahid.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/vahid.jpg" width="150" height="200" border="0" /><div class="caption">Vahid Nourani.</div></div><strong>Chad Custer</strong> (2003-04): <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/tact/jobinfo/vista7.html">Chad's project</a> to continue and expand <a href="http://www.duke.edu/web/isis/click/">CLICK</a>, was extended to Lyon's Park Community Center where Chad designed a complementary <a href="http://www.duke.edu/web/isis/click/lyonspark.html">curriculum</a> for younger students. CLICK materials are used by <a href="http://www.duke.edu/web/isis/click/locations.html">organizations across the nation</a>. </li>
  <li><strong>Vahid Nourani</strong> and <strong>Damita Chambers</strong> (2004-05): <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/tact/jobinfo/vista8-9.html">Their project</a> was to monitor, coordinate, and promote <a href="http://www.techlinkup.org">Tech LinkUp</a> and provide support for <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/techcoop">TechCoop</a> projects. Vahid also provided extensive technology support for <a href="http://www.unitedwaytriangle.org/t4t">Triangle United Way's Teaming for Technology (T4T)</a> as well as many local CTCs and other nonprofit organizations. Damita coordinated numerous activities and presentations for T4T and the <a href="http://list.nten.org/lists/info/501techclub-triangle">Triangle 501 Tech Club</a> and also coordinated the <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/rtpnet/rtpconf05/">6th Annual RTPnet Conference and Community Technology Awards</a>. Vahid is currently serving a second year as a CTC VISTA with Durham Literacy Center, while Damita continues service as a Public Ally with Alliance of AIDS Services Carolina. </li>
</ul>
<p>For RTPnet and the North Carolina communities we serve, CTC VISTAs have made an enormous difference.</p>
<HR>
<div class="bionote"><div class="float_left"><img alt="judy.gif" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/judy.gif" width="76" height="97" border="0" /></div><p><a href="mailto:hallman@rtpnet.org">Judith Huntress Hallman</a> (<a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/hallman/">http://www.rtpnet.org/hallman/</a>) is Executive Director and President of RTPnet and has worked as a volunteer for RTPnet since 1989.&nbsp; Judy provided computer support services at the <a href="http://www.unc.edu">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</a> (where she received a BA and MA in Mathematics), from 1967-1999. Her work included supervision of the Help Desk, training, documentation, and program development. When she <a href="http://www.unc.edu/news/gaz/archives/99feb24/file.10.html">retired</a> (March 1, 1999), she was Campus Webmaster. 
</p>
</div>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>RTPnet Adult Basic Computer Ed Handouts Available</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000373.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-27T04:00:02Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-27T00:00:02-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.373</id>
    <created>2005-10-27T04:00:02Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Read Hallman&apos;s full article:CTC VISTAs Strengthen RTPnet Links to revised handouts for four classes RTPnet has used (since 1996) to teach basic computer skills to adults were recently posted on the CTCNet members list and received several favorable reviews and...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Editor</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Networking</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p><div class="sidebar_right"><span class="subhead">Read Hallman's full article:</span><br><strong><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000362.html">CTC VISTAs Strengthen RTPnet</a></strong></div>
<a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/collections/comp.shtml">Links to revised handouts</a> for four classes RTPnet has used (since 1996) to teach basic computer skills to adults were recently posted on the CTCNet members list and received several favorable reviews and notes of appreciation. <a href="http://www.rtpnet.org/collections/handouts/overview.html">An overview</a> is available, too. The goal is to teach new users how to use a mouse, how to get around on the Internet and use email, and then how to continue learning using <a href="http://www.GCFLearnFree.org">GCFLearnFree</a>.</p>
<p>Handouts include step-by-step instructions and can be used by volunteer teachers who have not taught before. Students can take home the handouts and repeat on their own what was covered in class; typing has been minimized since many people who take these classes can't type. Paint is introduced in the first class because you don't need to type and it's fun.</p>
<p>If the content is useful but people prefer to use different software, <a href="mailto:hallman@rtpnet.org">Judy Hallman</a> has offered to provide additional assistance:</p>
<p> &quot;I'd be glad to modify what I have to create additional versions. Similarly, if there is a topic that is needed, let me know and I'll see what I can do.&nbsp; I really like <a href="http://www.myway.com">MyWay.com</a> for free email, but would be glad to also do yahoo, hotmail, and/or others if you find these are better services in some cases. My Way has a very short simple registration form with minimal typing required, no ads, good spam filters, and 125.0 MB.&quot;</p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Community History Helps TINCAN Create a Sense of Place in Spokane, WA</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000363.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-27T04:00:01Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-27T00:00:01-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.363</id>
    <created>2005-10-27T04:00:01Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[May Alm's WWII Nurses On a sunny afternoon in November 2004, World War II veterans gathered in a neighborhood caf&eacute; in Spokane, Washington, to tell their stories of war.&nbsp;&nbsp; A cake decorated as an American flag, donated by an area...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>Karen Michaelson</name>
      
      <email>kmichaelson@mail.sisna.com</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Networking</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p><div class="float_left"><img alt="tincan_ww2nurse.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/tincan_ww2nurse.jpg" width="250" height="291" border="0" /><div class="caption">May Alm's WWII Nurses</div></div>
On a sunny afternoon in November 2004, World War II veterans gathered in a neighborhood caf&eacute; in Spokane, Washington, to tell their stories of war.&nbsp;&nbsp; A cake decorated as an American flag, donated by an area grocery, greeted them as they signed in for the event.&nbsp; Each veteran was escorted to the back room of the caf&eacute;, where student volunteers helped them scan their photos and other memorabilia into laptops set up for the occasion and conducted oral history interviews. Leroy, one of the veterans attending the event commented, &ldquo;This is so much fun, I&rsquo;d like to keep talking all night.&rdquo;&nbsp; Many of the veterans made appointments for follow-up interviews.&nbsp; Some took information to tell their friends about the project.&nbsp; The volunteering students also became deeply involved. Lauren, a middle school student, asked her mother to postpone a movie date so that she and her friend could continue digitally processing a veteran&rsquo;s history.&nbsp; Lauren said, &ldquo;Mom, it was so cool learning about what really happened in World War II.&nbsp; Wow!&rdquo;</p>
<p><div class="float_right"><img alt="nora.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/nora.jpg" width="100" height="130" border="0" /><div class="caption">VISTA Nora Lollar</div></div>The event was the brainchild of Nora Lollar, a CTC AmeriCorps VISTA member with <a href="http://www.tincan.org/">The Inland Northwest Community Access Network</a> (TINCAN), who manages the Network&rsquo;s <a href="http://history.tincan.org">Inland Northwest Memories Project</a>.&nbsp; Under Nora's guidance, history collection and digital preservation have become catalysts for neighborhoods and organizations to gather, network, and learn more about their communities. &ldquo;When we started to populate the website last September,&rdquo; noted Lollar, &ldquo;we found communities and individuals willing to network together to learn new technology in order to save one of their most precious resources: their history.&rdquo; </p>
<p><a href="http://history.tincan.org">The Inland Northwest Memories Project (INMP)</a> has an online database archive of oral histories, photos, and other historical materials that makes the region's history easily available&mdash;to schools and local citizens especially. Based on the <a href="http://www.mainememory.net">Maine Memory Network website</a>, INMP has powerful search capacities as well as tools for classroom use.&nbsp; Museum and school people who want to become contributing members receive training in cataloging and uploading their materials.&nbsp; Teacher workshops are held for those who want to use local history in their classrooms.&nbsp; The INMP site was developed under a grant from the <a href="http://www.mainememory.net">National Endowment for the Humanities</a> but had been relatively unused until Lollar took over.&nbsp; Under her guidance, the site became a contributing member of the <a href="http://www.loc.gov/vets/">Library of Congress&rsquo; Veteran&rsquo;s project</a> and has expanded into neighborhood history and involved small community museums throughout the rural Inland Northwest.</p>
<div class="float_left"><img alt="tincan_foley.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/tincan_foley.jpg" width="250" height="420" border="0" /><div class="caption">Mike Bewer Foley 1917</div></div><p>INMP is a critical component of TINCAN&rsquo;s mission to build community resources in northeastern Washington &ldquo;&hellip;to provide education and support for social, economic, and community development through the use of computer technology and telecommunications. &ldquo;&nbsp; That mission is realized through (1) creating online content of value to the local community, (2) developing collaborative training and education with online resources, and 3) collaborating with our region&rsquo;s Community Technology Centers and other local partners to provide access to digital network technologies to those who might not otherwise be able to benefit from them.&nbsp; </p>
<p>As a community network, part of TINCAN&rsquo;s role is to help give our region&rsquo;s communities support in defining their identities.&nbsp; TINCAN has helped area students learn about the region&rsquo;s past and assisted neighborhoods and towns in developing economic development strategies that cohere with neighborhood values and lifestyles. When TINCAN began over eleven years ago, our primary mission was to provide access to computers and the Internet for those who would otherwise not have access due to poverty, minority status, or other disenfranchising circumstances.&nbsp; As access to information technology has grown, TINCAN&rsquo;s mission shifted to putting those technologies to use to benefit these same communities. TINCAN now provides continuing education for teachers, teen programs, and business development services. Following this trend, the Inland Northwest Memories Project has also become a catalyst for integrating a sense of place across TINCAN programs.&nbsp; In a related project funded by our local community foundation starting this fall, teens from Spokane&rsquo;s Garland district will collect oral histories and research other historical materials in an after-school program.&nbsp;&nbsp; These materials, once uploaded to INMP, will be the basis for four murals, designed with the assistance of professional artists recruited by an art gallery in the neighborhood.&nbsp; The teens will paint the murals on walls in the Garland Business District as part of their effort to convert the district from a humdrum declining business strip to a vibrant destination arts community.&nbsp; The whole process will be documented by the teens with videos and weblogs in TINCAN&rsquo;s <a href="http://votc.tincan.org/">Virtual Teen Center</a>.</p>
<div class="float_right"><img alt="tincan_arnold.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/tincan_arnold.jpg" width="193" height="263" border="0" /><div class="caption">Arnold A. McMullen</div></div><p>Lollar&rsquo;s work has involved students from many area schools and colleges in documenting local history.&nbsp; She coordinated a partnership with Summit School&rsquo;s 5th through 8th grade students and the Spokane Valley Heritage Museum to collect local history for the new museums first &ldquo;Founding Visionaries&rdquo; exhibit.&nbsp;&nbsp; A city-wide project for 2005-2006 grew out of that School&rsquo;s effort, where TINCAN, Summit, and the Spokane Valley museum will network to move an 1800&rsquo;s one-room school house to a site on the museum campus.&nbsp; This history gathering effort has the whole K-8 school and community working toward the common goal of collecting and preserving their regional history and enriching their city in the process. This activity has helped the newly incorporated City of Spokane Valley&rsquo;s find its identity. Lollar also is working with Spokane&rsquo;s Hillyard Museum, to put their collection online, before they even have a site for the museum in their economically depressed neighborhood. The Hillyard project is closely linked to their neighborhood revitalization as they build on their rich railroad history.&nbsp; TINCAN&rsquo;s INMP is playing a key role in creating an awareness of where these communities came from and where they are we going.&nbsp; &ldquo;This sense of 'place' is paramount as local communities make connections to appeal to businesses and people to their area,&rdquo; said Lollar.</p>
<p>Lollar has built a strong base of volunteers for the project that will help it endure, and will bolster TINCAN&rsquo;s presence as a community network in the region.&nbsp; INMP has been integrated into history classes at two area colleges, <a href="http://www.gonzaga.edu">Gonzaga University</a> and <a href="ww.whitworth.edu">Whitworth College</a> where students gather local historical materials on the topics being covered each year in the urban and public history classes.&nbsp; Similarly, several high schools have added a collection of historical materials by students into their curriculum. The TINCAN project has collected and preserved literally hundreds of historical treasures that would otherwise be lost. And Lollar states: &ldquo;&hellip;and the best part is we&rsquo;ve only begun.&rdquo;</p>
<HR>
<p><div class="bionote"><div class="float_left"><img alt="kmichaelson.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/kmichaelson.jpg" width="115" height="113" border="0" /></div>
<a href="mailto:kmichaelson@sisna.com">Karen L. Michaelson</a>, Ph.D., is Executive Director of <a href="http://www.tincan.org/">the Inland Northwest Community Access Network</a> (TINCAN), in Spokane, Washington.</p><p>&nbsp;</p><p>&nbsp;</div></p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ed Schwartz: Community Organizing and Development</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000364.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-26T04:00:08Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-26T00:00:08-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.364</id>
    <created>2005-10-26T04:00:08Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[(see Focusing the Work of CTC VISTA Projects&mdash;Priority Area Presentations) Ed Schwartz. Community organizing and development is a priority area that may permeate the missions of many CTC VISTA Project technology centers, and indeed CTCs in general.&nbsp;&nbsp; This area also...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>Danielle Martin</name>
      
      <email>danielle@umb.edu</email>
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Organizing and Development</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>(see <a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000343.html">Focusing the Work of CTC VISTA Projects&mdash;Priority Area Presentations</a>)</strong></p>
<p><div class="float_right"><img alt="ed_pso.jpg" src="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/ed_pso.jpg" width="200" height="269" border="0" /><div class="caption">Ed Schwartz.</div></div>
Community organizing and development is a priority area that may permeate the missions of many CTC VISTA Project technology centers, and indeed CTCs in general.&nbsp;&nbsp; This area also has a large amount of references, sources and contacts &mdash; so much so that it may seem daunting. </p>
<p>Ed Schwartz, author of <strong><em>NetActivism: How Citizens Use the Internet</em></strong><strong></strong>and founder/director of the <a href="http://www.iscv.org">Institute for Study of Civic Values</a>, broaches the massive amount of information in the context of the Institute's mission of &ldquo;demonstrating &hellip;how to build community and examine public policy within the framework of principles set forth in the Declaration of Independence and the Preamble to the Constitution.&rdquo;&nbsp; Given this framework, Ed has designed the <a href="http://neighborhoodsonline.net">Neighborhoods Online</a> website as an accessible doorway for concerned citizens to enter the wide web world of civic information.&nbsp; It is not only an easy-to-navigate gateway to the enormous amount of usually cumbersome civic and government websites, but it is also a resource organized specifically for civic organizing and activism by blocks, neighborhoods, and cities. </p>
<p><div class="sidebar_right">
  <span class="subhead">More Resources related to the Community Organizing and Development priority area:</span>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000354.html">Ten Web Sites to Help Profile a Community</a></li>
    <li><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000353.html">Community Organizing and Development in the <em>ComTechReview</em> Archives</a></li>
  </ul>
</div><a href="http://www.phillyneighborhoods.org">Phillyneighborhoods.org</a> is the richest example of its application, filled with resources for community activists and projects that Ed has been involved with for so many years in his own hometown.&nbsp; Using a handy set of top &ldquo;ten websites to profile a community&rdquo; (see sidebar), Ed shows how the information can be reorganized for local organizing purposes, including demonstrating the local extent and effect of budget cuts in federal programs that often seem so distant and unrelated to actual lives.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.phillyneighborhoods.org">Phillyneighborhoods.org</a> has information organized for blocks and neighborhoods with the goal of helping to educate and organize interested citizens around issues such as safety in schools and the cost of crime.&nbsp; It has menu options and content areas in housing, crime, education, jobs, recreation, health, and human services. This kind of portal is a unique resource for citizens scanning the enormous amount of unorganized community information that is often untapped through the Internet because it is so hard to find and not organized or formatted for civic engagement and community development purposes.</p>
<p>The Institute's recently-launched Ten Point <a href="http://www.phillyneighborhoods.org/civicvalues">Civic Value Campaign</a> is aimed at helping neighborhood organizations work with government and schools to strengthen civic values and resources in these areas. By using tools such as <a href="http://neighborhoodsonline.net">Neighborhoods Online</a>, citizens can be galvanized to &ldquo;make government work&rdquo; and use available data to profile their own communities and support campaigns to improve local schools, businesses and street corners.</p>
<p>&mdash;<em>Danielle Martin </em></p>]]>
      A Summary from the CTC VISTA Project Pre-service Orientation for new VISTAs and Supervisors, August 31, 2005 
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ten Web Sites to Help Profile a Community</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000354.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-26T04:00:07Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-26T00:00:07-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.354</id>
    <created>2005-10-26T04:00:07Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain"><![CDATA[ NeighborhoodsOnline.Net &mdash; the Institute for the Study of Civic Value's web site that includes links to all the links suggested below. Census Bureau - includes demographic data at the census tract, community, city, county, and state level; at the...]]></summary>
    <author>
      <name>Editor</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Organizing and Development</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<ol>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.neighborhoodsonline.net">NeighborhoodsOnline.Net</a> &mdash;</strong> the <a href="http://www.iscv.org">Institute for the Study of Civic Value</a>'s web site that includes links to all the links suggested below.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.census.gov">Census Bureau</a></strong> - includes demographic data at the census tract, community, city, county, and state level; at <a href="http://www.census.gov/main/www/cen2000.html">the 2000 census gateway</a>, you can even get information related to a specific address.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.statelocalgov.net/">The State and Local Government Web Site</a></strong> - an easy-to-use online portal to every town, county, city, and state government website in the United States. When you get into individual web sites, read the Mayor's State of the City address will give you a fast look at the major issues facing the community.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.newslink.org">NewsLink</a></strong>- indexes newspapers and broadcast stations by city. Want to read the local paper? This website links to all of them.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.hud.gov/offices/cpd/about/conplan/local/index.cfm">Local Consolidated HUD Plans</a></strong>- Local and state governments that receive Community Development Block Grant Funding from HUD must submit specific plans documenting the level of poverty and housing, along with a description of the programs that will be used to address it. These plans represent a virtual guide to hardship in America.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.bls.gov/bls/regnhome.htm">Bureau of Labor Statistics - Regional Economic Data</a></strong> &ndash; BLS's page that tracks data by region; it provides some indication of the economic condition of the cities and communities within each region.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.census.gov/govs/www/cffr.html">Federal Spending by County</a></strong> - What is the total federal investment in a county, including entitlements like Social Security and Medicare, grant programs like VISTA and the Head Start, research funding, and salaries of the federal employees working in the county? This little known Census Bureau data site provides information for every county in the United States between 1993 and 2003. As the debate over the federal budget unfolds, this website enables you to make the connections locally.&nbsp; Also check out Ed&rsquo;s site: <a href="http://www.bushbudget.com/">BushBudget.com</a>.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.vote-smart.org">Vote-Smart</a></strong> &mdash; still the best web site to get comprehensive information about state and federal representatives throughout the country.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://groups.yahoo.com">Yahoo Groups</a></strong>- the most widely used listserv service by civic groups, covering a wide range of issues. </li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.google.com">Google</a></strong> &ndash; Yes, we know, you already use Google. &nbsp;But it still deserves a place here as the best search engine for anything else you're trying to find in a city or community.</li>
</ol>
]]>
      Community Organizing and Development: 
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Community Organizing and Development in the CTR Archives</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/000353.html" />
    <modified>2005-10-26T04:00:06Z</modified>
    <issued>2005-10-26T00:00:06-05:00</issued>
    <id>tag:www.comtechreview.org,2005:/fall-2005//16.353</id>
    <created>2005-10-26T04:00:06Z</created>
    <summary type="text/plain">Spring-Summer 2005 Community Networking: Movements in the Field and at the Radical Center by Michael Maranda Houston&apos;s Technology for All Wireless Project and the National Municipal Wireless Debate by Will Reed The Foundation of Community Information Technology: Community-Based Research by...</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Editor</name>
      
      
    </author>
    <dc:subject>Community Organizing and Development</dc:subject>
    <content type="text/html" mode="escaped" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-2005/">
      <![CDATA[<p><div class="subhead">Spring-Summer 2005</div></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000318.html">Community Networking: Movements in the Field and at the Radical Center</a><em> by Michael Maranda </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000330.html">Houston's Technology for All Wireless Project and the National Municipal Wireless Debate</a><em> by Will Reed </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000311.html">The Foundation of Community Information Technology: Community-Based Research</a><em> by Randy Stoecker </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000326.html">Book Review of <em>Research Methods for Community Change: A Project-Based Approach</em></a><em> by Melissa C. Jeter</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000327.html">Book Review of <em>Community Practice in the Network Society: Local Action/Global Interaction</em></a><em> by Daniel Schackman</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000309.html">New Immigrants and Internet Use: Crossing Borders for Social and Cultural Benefit</a><em> by Corry Bregendahl and Cornelia Flora </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000295.html">'Bringing IT Home' with the Cleveland Housing Network</a><em> by DeJuan Perrymond </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000298.html">CDBG-supported Programs at Toledo's Murchison Center</a> <em>by James Moseby </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000321.html">e-Literacy and Connectivity for Development in India, the Akshaya Approach</a><em> by Joyojeet Pal and G.R. Kiran</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-summer-2005/000322.html">eSeva E-services in Southeast India</a> <em>by Sanjay Jaju</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Winter 2004-2005</div></p>
<p>Book Review: <a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000228.html">Shaping the Network Society: The New Role of Civil Society in Cyberspace</a><em> by Daniel Schackman</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000261.html">The Power of All of Us? &mdash; The eBay Lesson for Community Development</a><em> by Frank Odasz</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000254.html">Public Policy, Online Content, and Research to Expand Community Access to Digital Opportunities</a><em> by Wendy Lazarus and Laurie Lipper</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000255.html">e-Lection: Using Technology to Involve Communities in the Election Process</a><em> by Oscar Madrigal and James Lau</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000280.html">e-Liberate &mdash; A New Tool for Online Deliberation</a><em> by Doug Schuler</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-2004-2005/000257.html">Blogging for Your Community</a><em> by Trudy Schuett</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Summer 2004</div></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000188.html">Emergence, Convergence, and Empowerment</a><em> by Daniel Schackman</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2004/000182.html">Community Development and Technology 2004 Conference Track sessions</a></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Winter-Spring 2004</div></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2004/000181.html">The Boston Earned Income Tax Credit Electronic Filing and Technology Access Project</a><em> by Joan Arches </em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Summer 2003</div></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/summer-2003/000011.html">Using GIS Mapping to Build Community</a><em> by Megan Kinney and Michael Clark</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Spring 2003</div></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/spring-2003/000048.html">An Illinois Consortium at the Digital Crossroads</a><em> by Layton Olsen</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Fall-Winter 2002-2003</div></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000112.html">Mapping and Community Organizing in Philadelphia</a><em> by Eric Hoffman</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000113.html">Edna Jackson, Technology And Community Building: From Staunchest Opponent to Greatest Proponent</a><em> by Randal Pinkett</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/fall-02_winter-03/000107.html">From The Children's Partnership: Strategies and Resources for Community Technology Practitioners</a><em> by Laurie Lipper and Wendy Lazarus</em></p>
<p><div class="subhead">Winter-Spring 2002</div></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000058.html">Community Mapping for Neighborhood Knowledge in Los Angeles</a><em> by Bill Pitkin and Nick Rattray</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000065.html">Contentbank.org: Content-Building for and<em> by Local Communities</a><em> by Laurie Lipper and Francisco Mora</em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.comtechreview.org/winter-spring-2002/000068.html">Buenos Aires, Montreal, and Seattle: Civic Unrest and Civic Intelligence</a><em> by Doug Schuler</em></p>]]>
      
    </content>
  </entry>

</feed>